<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Noumenal Notions</title>
    <link>https://noumenalnotions.space/</link>
    <description>&lt;no value&gt;</description>
    <language>en</language>
    <atom:link href="https://noumenalnotions.space/tags/religion/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <generator>Hugo</generator>

    
    <item>
      <title>On the Necessity of Mediation</title>
      <link>https://noumenalnotions.space/essays/on_the_necessity_of_mediation/</link>
      <guid>https://noumenalnotions.space/essays/on_the_necessity_of_mediation/</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 18 May 2025 13:06:44 IST</pubDate>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;My encounter with the works of Kant and Hume thrust me in a direction I seldom anticipated. Although I was acquainted with the idea of the &amp;ldquo;unknowable&amp;rdquo; written about in many great religions and myths, somehow Kant&amp;rsquo;s formulation of the noumenon made it for me a living reality. Something we can no longer evade under the pretext of dismissing age old superstitions because Kant justified its existence through purely rational means. However I remained unconvinced that it was simply the idea of the &amp;ldquo;unknowable&amp;rdquo; that had gripped me so tenaciously. Notwithstanding the fact that Kant provided many arguments vying for the noumenal world, it was still unclear what relevance it had in our earthly pursuits. By delineating the frontiers of human knowledge, Kant has once and for all given us the map beyond which no pursuit of truth could ever take place. And this seems to be its only consequence. The unknowable permeates all of life and despite our most ardent efforts, we shall forever remain ignorant of the true nature of the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given that fact, it seems natural to simply content ourselves with matters where do we have a say, taking each step in view of our abject limitations. As much as Kant had formulated a problem central to the study of philosophy, this was the reaction he prevalently elicited. If the &amp;ldquo;unknowable&amp;rdquo; by its very definition cannot be understood in any meaningful sense, why does its existence even matter? In other words regardless of the fact that you believe all of reality can or cannot be known, you would conduct yourself all the same. Although I was thoroughly convinced of the paramount importance of Kant&amp;rsquo;s worldview, I could go no further than this in stating its relevance. Clearly the noumenon is of paramount importance in illuminating the nature of reality but in matters of practice where we are faced with the choice between good and bad, it appears to have little to say.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This problem of choosing in the absence of certainty, especially when the choice itself concerned another individual is, in my opinion, the one of the fundamental problems of morality. Although Kant had attempted to formulate an ethical philosophy in his second publication &amp;ldquo;Critique of Practical Reason&amp;rdquo;, I found the works of another great thinker far more insightful in this respect. Being a profound admirer and an astute student of Kant&amp;rsquo;s work, Schopenhauer had done for more than any philosopher to elaborate on the former&amp;rsquo;s worldview. And he did this mostly by pointing out the fundamental error in Kant&amp;rsquo;s perception of the noumenal. According to Schopenhauer, Kant viewed the noumenon from a purely conceptual lens and rightly derived its implications in the realm of thought. However in the sphere of immediate experience, we encountered the noumenon in stark lucidity. As much the distinctions we have made to understand the nature of the world mire us in endless paradoxes, Schopanhaeur believed in direct experience a knowledge of the noumenon could still be attainable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It would be a misnomer to call this &amp;ldquo;knowledge&amp;rdquo;, as the noumenon negates the very preconditions of understanding. Knowledge presupposes differentiation and any potential experience of the unknowable annihilates that, leaving no room for thought itself. Unlike his predecessors, Schopenhauer ascribed profound significance to the arts because he believed it was the primary means through which we obtained this knowledge. He proposed that art and especially music allowed us to transcend the limitations of the phenomenal, creating almost a fissure in time and space where we could glimpse, however fleetingly, at the unknowable. I considered this as an insight of particular genius because on some fundamental sense, it shed light on the motivations of all human beings. I could see the operation of this instinct to grasp the &amp;ldquo;unknowable&amp;rdquo; not only in art but in almost every human endeavour. The greatest of writers, artists and poets invariably proceeded on the tacit recognition that the substance of their work was always too narrowly confined by their medium of expression. Therefore through the creation of art, they perennially endeavoured to articulate the ineffable. To show the immeasurable distance between the world of representations and the world of actual things. Or rather the actual thing &amp;ldquo;in itself&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the existence of this distance also posed a peculiar danger. Despite the fact that a work of art allows us to pierce through the veil of the phenomenal, it still remains momentary. In light of this, it is tempting to conclude that most of life is simply a pursuit of the noumenal. An attempt to steal a glimpse at the ultimate mystery in moments scattered across time. Nonetheless it is important to remember that as much as the noumenon is a testament to the fundamental unity of all individuals, this unity is achieved by a complete eradication of differences. Differences necessary for the genesis of life itself. Therefore the very conditions of existence emerges at a crossroad. In a cradle of the primordial paradox where we are faced with two opposing instincts, one of which beckons us into the noumenal abyss while the other cautions us from being swallowed by it. The consequence of this polarity, of the need to apprehend the perennial void from the realm of what is known produces the vagaries of living. Every effort we have made since the dawn of civilization consequently serves as a monument to capture this mystery. An attempt to instantiate, atleast symbolically, the primordial calling that lies at the heart of man.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But what of the danger? In virtue of our existential positioning, we remain tethered both to the unknowable and to the ephemeral world of our senses. Kant was able to justify the concept of free will within a deterministic world because he believed our existence could not be fully encapsulated by phenomena. As much this explained human feelings such as compassion and love, it also revealed a deeper problem. Although we have grown accustomed to judging truth and falsehood by taking recourse to our senses, we cannot deny the fact that we are children of two distinct worlds. Worlds not wherein we exist but those that arise in virtue of our existence. Our situation is further complicated by our inability to obtain even the faintest of knowledge about one of these worlds. Something we have termed as the &amp;ldquo;noumenon&amp;rdquo;. Despite art providing us with a conduit to fleetingly apprehend this in experience, we can never obtain any total understanding of it and therefore remain ignorant of both the noumenon and consequently to a part of ourselves. Torn between these worlds, logic would necessitate confining our pursuits to the world of sensory apprehension. And since the advent of science this is the path we are encouraged to take. The path of reason, illumination and sober empiricism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a result, the contemporary landscape is characterized by an exaltation of the phenomenal. Even outside the laboratory of the scientist, rigorous experimentation has generally become the way of life. The world of today refuses to believe anything without resorting to the stock of experience, relegating notions of faith to the antiquities of the past. But in their place a new form of crass materialism has taken root. The unmitigated progress of science that epitomized rationality has paradoxically also constricted the horizons of an individual. The skepticism which was once a luminary in the pursuit of truth has now become mere pretense to remain ensconced in the luxurious comfort of the sensory world. Therefore in the place of meaning, we now seek opulence. In the place of truth, we remain content with certainty. In the name of progress and the vilification of the doctrines of the old, we have abandoned the unknowable not as a concept but as an enduring facet of human experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Art is perhaps the only relic of the past that remains where we become faintly aware of other modes of knowing but even that is momentary. The distance between the noumenal and the phenomenal is either too far removed so the former becomes nothing more than a bleak reminder of our limitations or it is entirely annihilated so the individual is subsumed by that which he apprehends. In both cases however, the consequences remain more or less the same. We come to blatantly deny the incommensurable conflict at the heart of being that makes us both a part of a whole and the whole itself. Faced with such a seemingly insoluble problem, we make a myriad of choices. And those reactions to the unknowable, ultimately, defines the course of our lives. In view of our individual differences, it is difficult to arrive at any viable means to discern these choices in terms of &amp;ldquo;good&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;bad&amp;rdquo;. To reasonably conclude what one &amp;ldquo;should&amp;rdquo; do in the face of the noumenon. But in another sense, there still appears to be a general answer to this problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Much like Schopenhauer&amp;rsquo;s understanding of the arts, the morality that emerges from our existential roots is largely devoid of rhetoric. Given our two fold nature, I think what remains to be discovered in the course of living is a process of mediation between our dichotomous roots. Similar to the immutable laws of music that distinguishes sound from rhythm, there appears to be a certain movement through life that cuts through the phenomenal and the noumenal. This movement is both general and specific and evolves quite similarly to a piece of music where the notes periodically converge to a point of symphony, eventually assuming their own individual paths. Through this light, morality appears as an attempt to liberate art from its temporal confines. To essentially trace the rhythm of life which expresses our noumenal and phenomenal nature in its entirety. As much as a study of ethics enlightens this perspective, it seems that a true understanding of morality consists of learning to hear the music rather than reading its notes. Without the melody of experience morality devolves into a science of platitudes. And without sober reflection art becomes a vessel of escape rather than a means of enlightenment. Therefore the fundamental task of art and morality appears to be one and the same. To offer a guiding lantern in the face of the primeval darkness that engulfs us all.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Should You Use the Commandline?</title>
      <link>https://noumenalnotions.space/blogs/should_you_use_the_commandline/</link>
      <guid>https://noumenalnotions.space/blogs/should_you_use_the_commandline/</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 04 May 2025 09:02:04 IST</pubDate>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A large part of Linux might seem daunting to a novice user because it involves the command line. Unlike Windows or MacOS where the graphical interface is intertwined with the operating system itself, Linux&amp;rsquo;s GUI is simply another package that is installed. The system can function just the same without it because at its core it relies on something called &amp;ldquo;tty&amp;rdquo; to communicate with the user. Essentially ttys are virtual emulations of an old device called teletype which was used as one of the first input/output mechanism for computers. Although originally users communicated with computers primarily through text, we have come to replace this with a more appealing visual interface as it was easier to learn and navigate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This course of events merits little explanation because using the tty required a reasonable grasp of commands and how the system itself functioned. The general public would not have been particularly enticed by the necessity of having to learn commands and syntax just so that they could use these machines. Most operating systems, as a result, have come to entirely replace this mechanism with a visual interface, making tty, even if it existed in certain systems, only a vestige of the past. Linux, on the other hand, still retained this part of history. One of the first things you would see when you install a minimal Linux distribution is just a black screen with a blinking white cursor, patiently waiting for you to programmatically express your will. Graphical interfaces are installed on top of this but you could still communicate with your system even in the absence of such mediation just like how you would 60 years ago.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Coming from a world where immersive visual experience is heralded as the biggest achievement of technology, this kind of decision appears a little strange. One would generally expect the whole practice of using ttys to be relegated into the past once computers became capable of rendering visual graphics. However, with Linux the command line continued to survive. Although users still preferred to use a &amp;ldquo;terminal emulator&amp;rdquo; within a graphical environment, the necessity to communicate with computers textually did not wane in the least. On the contrary, most Linux users prefer to use the terminal over GUI despite the latter&amp;rsquo;s aesthetic appeal.  Why exactly might this be?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From a purely technical perspective, using the terminal to interact with the operating system provides more control. A certain subset of users like programmers and developers might prefer this fine tuned approach because for their use, textual interactions are far more salutary. However, as I had implied, Linux users regardless of their technical expertise come to develop a particular affinity towards the terminal, eventhough it appears painfully tedious. My initial experience with Linux provoked similar feelings and as I had grown to nurture that very affinity, the reasons behind it had only become more inexplicable. I constantly found myself asking, and perhaps still do, that why exactly did I use the command line?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Answering this question, at the outset, brought into consideration all the different ways terminals are better than GUIs. Although learning commands and their syntax might prove to be difficult initially, with a little persistence any task you perform with a computer becomes blazingly fast. From copying files to downloading programs, whatever effort you expend typing commands stays more or less the same regardless of the magnitude of the task itself. And this scalability of commands is, in my opinion, one of its biggest advantages. And with shell features like aliasing and scripting almost any series of tasks can be automated. Given the fact that you are willing to learn and forsake expedience for some time, the possibilities of this world are endless.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although mastering the command line requires years of practice, obtaining a fair understanding of it can be done rather quickly. And unlike the general impression, learning commands does not require any kind of formal expertise as a programmer. However it does demand sustained curiosity and here is where the ways of men part. Some users might regard computers as simply a means to an end so they might not be inclined for such adventures. For such people the GUIs in Linux are good enough for most of their use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However it is important to remember that the visual interface as much as it simplifies also veils what is underneath a system. It limits the possibilities of what a user can or cannot do, sometimes making errors themselves virtually undiagnosable. As much as Linux mitigates this, it is a problem that arises with the creation of GUI itself as simplification entails relinquishing control over to someone who does the simplifying. A subset of users, I believe, are fundamentally disenchanted by this process, making ttys the means through which they peer into the visual facade.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although both GUIs and terminals coexist in most Linux systems, the latter still remains the primary channel for any user interaction. And more than providing control, such unmediated channels enlarge the possibility of creative expression. Any part of the system can be changed, erased or used in combination in any way that is deemed necessary. More than being machines that passively receive input, for these users computers become the tools through which they explore the world. Thefore every Linux system, far from being generic, unmistakbly bears the imprints of its user. Through customizations or the mere writing of scripts and programs, each system eventually becomes tailored to the needs and preferences of its user. And this kind of invovled personal computing is primarily why I use the command line but to the question of wether you should use it, I leave that entirely up to you.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Introduction to SSH</title>
      <link>https://noumenalnotions.space/blogs/introduction_to_ssh/</link>
      <guid>https://noumenalnotions.space/blogs/introduction_to_ssh/</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 27 Apr 2025 09:01:55 IST</pubDate>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;SSH is a word that you might often see thrown around when talking about servers and connections. It is sometimes used as a noun in sentences but also as a verb. Its colloquial and sometimes unconventional usage in certain contexts might leave you confused on what exactly it means. Is it a program or does it denote an action that we do? Well, its technically the former. SSH abbreviates to &amp;ldquo;Secure Shell&amp;rdquo; and it is a program written by Tatu Ylonen to serve as a replacement to the telnet program. Ever since the early days of computing, users often found it necessary to connect to another computer from their local machine. This computer, often called a server, had specific pathways or ports open for users to establish a connection if they had the proper credentials. Telnet was widely used in these early stages but one of its biggest problems was that it transmitted all data in clear text.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This essentially meant that any malicious actor sniffing the traffic could not only intercept the credentials of the user but also any information that was being passed to and fro. Telent had to be relegated to the past primarily for this reason which made way for its faster and more secure replacement, SSH. The Secure Shell program brought in several mechanisms to address the limitations of telnet. It introduced asymmetric encryption so that all the traffic remained indecipherable. It also protected the integrity of the data that was being transmitted, while also providing alternate ways of authentication. Within a few years of its inception, ssh was adopted worldwide as the de facto standard to establish connections to servers. However unlike its daunting capabilities, using ssh is quite straightforward.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have ssh installed on any operating system, you can access it by opening the terminal and simply typing &amp;ldquo;ssh&amp;rdquo;.
You would most likely see an output quite similar to this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;usage: ssh [-46AaCfGgKkMNnqsTtVvXxYy] [-B bind_interface] [-b bind_address]
           [-c cipher_spec] [-D [bind_address:]port] [-E log_file]
           [-e escape_char] [-F configfile] [-I pkcs11] [-i identity_file]
           [-J destination] [-L address] [-l login_name] [-m mac_spec]
           [-O ctl_cmd] [-o option] [-P tag] [-p port] [-R address]
           [-S ctl_path] [-W host:port] [-w local_tun[:remote_tun]]
           destination [command [argument ...]]
       ssh [-Q query_option]
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;This enumerates all the different parameters that ssh provides. You would not be needing most of this when you simply want to connect to a server. The syntax for establishing an ssh connection in its generic sense is &amp;ldquo;ssh user_name@domain_name/ip&amp;rdquo;. If for example I want to connect to the server jetbrains.org with the username martian the syntax would be:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;ssh martian@jetbrains.org&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Depending on the server, this would prompt for a password or directly drop us into a shell if public key authentication is configured. The ip of the server can also be used instead of the domain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;ssh martian@100.54.11.24&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is all the syntax you would need most of the time when connecting to a server. There can be instances where a server is not running its open ssh daemon (a background process listening for connections) on port 22 and the aforementioned commands assume this port when establishing a connection.  In cases where the server is listening for ssh connections in a different port the syntax will have to be slightly modified with the -p flag.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;ssh martian@jetbrains.org -p 2121&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The flag slightly modifies the behaviour of the command so that it connects to the ssh daemon running on port 2121 in the server. Most users who regularly connect to servers through ssh find it tedious to enter their passwords each time. As I had fleetingly mentioned, SSH also allows for a form of authentication called Public Key and this is mostly what is used. This form of authentication works on the basis of assymetric encryption. On their local machines, users generate a key pair using the command&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;ssh-keygen -t ed25519&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The -t flag specifies the kind of keys you want to create which in this case is &amp;ldquo;ed25519&amp;rdquo; but ssh also provides other formats. After issuing the command, the user will be prompted to decide the location of the key and a passphrase. Although the passphrase can be left empty, using one provides better protection as it requires the user to enter the passphrase everytime the keys are used. After this stage, two keys will be generated with the designated name and one of the keys will have a &amp;ldquo;.pub&amp;rdquo; extension. For instance:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;secure_ssh_key secure_ssh_key.pub&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Any kind of information encrypted by one key can only be decrypted by the other and this is the foundation of assymetric encryption. Once both the keys are generated the &amp;ldquo;ssh-copy-id&amp;rdquo; command can be used to copy the public key to the server.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;ssh-copy-id -i secure_ssh_key.pub martian@jetbrains.org&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The -i flag denotes the path to the public key that is to be copied to the server. This command only works if the secure_ssh_key.pub file is in the current directory. If the keys are stored elswhere, change to that directory or simply provide the full path to the -i flag. Once the command is executed, the user will be able to authenticate to the server without a password using the command&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;ssh -i secure_ssh_key martian@jetbrains.org&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The -i flag denotes the path to the private key that was generated. If the name of the key was left to the default, the -i flag is most likely not required. However if the name has been changed, -i must be specified to instruct the command which private key to use. Some users might copy the same public key for all their server while others might generate a new one for each of them. Regardless of your choice, it might be wise to use the ~/.ssh/config file to manage all your different servers and keys. Each entry in the file takes the form of:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;Host jetb
	HostName jetbrains.org
	User martian
	Port 22
	IdentityFile ~/.ssh/secure_ssh_key
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;Host refers to the term I would use to connect to the server. Hostname is the actual domain or the ip of the server. User and Port are self explanatory and IdentityFile is the path to my private key. With this entry in ~/.ssh/config I can simply connect to jetbrains.org with the following command:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;ssh jetb&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This would automatically look for the host &amp;ldquo;jetb&amp;rdquo; in config file and apply all the specifications required to make the connection. Although programs like anydesk allow you to perform similar functions through a GUI, using ssh is certainly more immersive. With a few keystrokes you are literally inside a computer that could be millions of miles away and any initial experience of that is nothing less than magical.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For a novice user ssh might be his first introduction into the world of UNIX so the syntax might seem a little cryptic at first. I think it is important to understand that each command and its syntax have a clear underlying logic to them that can be applied to other commands. The arguments and flags might vary but the essential structure itself remains the same. So this is partly not just an introduction to ssh but also to how commands themselves are in the UNIX world.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What is a Linux Distribution?</title>
      <link>https://noumenalnotions.space/blogs/what_is_a_distribution/</link>
      <guid>https://noumenalnotions.space/blogs/what_is_a_distribution/</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Apr 2025 09:01:46 IST</pubDate>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;If you have been persuaded by my argument to use Linux or atleast to see for yourself if any of my comparisons hold water, perhaps the first confusion that might arise is why are there so many flavours of Linux? I had mentioned previously that &amp;ldquo;Linux&amp;rdquo; strictly speaking in and of itself is not an operating system. What we refer to as Linux is only the kernel which essentially is the core of an operating system on top of which other utilities are added to make it useable. These utilities, in our context, belong to the GNU (GNU is Not UNIX) foundation which incorporated the Linux kernel to produce what is properly called as the GNU/Linux operating system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To digress a little, the GNU foundation was started by Richard Stallman an American programmer who wanted to create an operating system like UNIX without any of its proprietary code. Stallman had started his foundation to rewrite most of the core utilities found in UNIX under a license where the software could be freely and openly distributed. The foundation, however, was persistently troubled by the development of a proper kernel until Linus Trovalds entered the picture, with his new pet project. Perhaps through luck or sheer happenstance, the meeting of both these projects birthed one of the most influential operating systems to have existed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since the kernel itself was developed in isolation and remained unfettered by a monolithic operating system, it allowed for the possibility to package the Linux kernel differently, keeping in mind the various needs and preferences of the user. This is what produced the plethora of Linux distributions that often overwhelms a user in his forays into the world of UNIX. But most distributions that exist are essentially &amp;ldquo;forks&amp;rdquo; or derivatives of 3 major flavours: Debian, Fedora and Arch. These distributions come with different package managers and adopt fundamentally different philosophies on what constitutes the ideal distribution. Debian and Fedora for instance place an emphasis on stability whereas Arch is willing to make some compromises on it to provide quick updates to its users. The distributions are managed by a host of maintainers who are responsible for the overseeing the distribution&amp;rsquo;s core repositories and its releases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It might seem quite surprising for novel users to discover that such elaborate mechanisms governing the release and the management of these various flavours of Linux are brought about by sheer collaboration. A significant proportion of contributors who help these distributions grow are not in any way financially rewarded for their support. The ethos of this community is heavily colored by a sense of understanding and respect its members hold for each other, making collaboration a product of not obligation but a concern to return the favour. The organic nature of this process is what propelled the development of these distributions in the absence of any large scale corporate oversight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the question still remains, which Linux distribution might be the most ideal for you? For a person with little to no understanding of the internal workings of a computer, any derivative based on Debian and Fedora might be a reasonable choice. Distributions like Ubuntu, Pop OS, Linux Mint come with a graphical environment post installation, which makes it somewhat intuitive to a user formerly mired by Windows all his life. These distributions can also be dual booted, a process where two or more operating systems can be used in one or multiple storage devices attached to a computer. Dual booting can be somewhat tricky to implement with distributions whose installers require a manual configuration of partitions. With the little distributions I have used, Ubuntu&amp;rsquo;s installer comes with an option to install Ubuntu alongside Windows so no manual configuration is required in that case.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite the sheer number of distributions available some of which might appeal to your uncanny tastes and sensibilities, it would be prescient to choose a flavour with a fairly large community. Stable distributions with a wide user base will mostly not cause problems with regular use. However there are instances where even such distributions pose issues in which case community support would help immensely. Whatever your choice of distribution maybe, I think it is important to remember that the growth and the maintenance of distributions is largely a social process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using a particular flavour of Linux puts you in a position where you have a shared experience with millions of users the world over. In communal spaces, these users often exchange ideas and insights pertaining to improvements that can be made or issues persistently bothering them. Sometimes you even find them talking about technology or even life in general. In my experience it has always been fruitful to engage in these communities not only for the support they offer when you are struggling with problems but also that its often nice to meet people who share your interests and even technical issues that might at times make you feel you are the only person in the entire world cursed with such a problem. I assure you, you are not.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>That Which We Seek</title>
      <link>https://noumenalnotions.space/essays/that_which_we_seek/</link>
      <guid>https://noumenalnotions.space/essays/that_which_we_seek/</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Apr 2025 21:45:26 IST</pubDate>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It has become unfashionable to use religious language to describe any human experience. I believe the disrepute religion has fallen into over time is not entirely due to prejudice or blind disdain. It was widely felt that the understanding once afforded by the frameworks of faith was subordinate to that of reason. I have found myself in the crossroads of both these sides, unable to give up one for the other. However I am still far more sympathetic to the pursuit of truth and prefer its uncertainty to the comfort of staunch belief. Yet despite such sympathies, I have also found that I take recourse to mystical notions when I try to grapple with problems of deep significance. Words belonging to the religious fold such as &amp;ldquo;curse&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;sin&amp;rdquo; seemed to me animated despite my recognition of its dubious metaphysical foundations. It seemed natural to ask what was so special about these words that they often impressed themselves upon me. And to ask whenever I pursued a line of thought deep enough why did I often reach a point where language and rationality ceased to be the luminaries they once were. At the deepest of my reflections, I was invariably surrounded by a blackness where no differentiation existed. Where no categories could be drawn. Where no thought could arise in solid footing. I sought refuge in these arcane words because they were the closest forms of expression I could find in communicating something so real and yet so nebulous. I could not see or touch this blackness but it certainly underpinned all of what I thought or felt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As far as my understanding of knowledge was concerned, the source of this experience seemed atleast partially comprehensible. Observations that we make of the world and of ourselves are fundamentally tentative. A philosopher of great renown named David Hume, coined this as the problem of induction. He demonstrated, through reasoning, that our observation of event B followed by event A does not necessarily indicate a causal relationship between them. Despite observing both of these events follow one an other, there still exists possibilities of observation that might entirely contradict all previous knowledge of those events. Therefore any statement that posits causality is by nature an assumption. An assumption that holds water in our daily lives but an assumption nonetheless. Accepting this proposition entailed a defeat in the quest to achieve knowledge that was certain. If statements based on observations, despite being validated for millenia, could still be open to contradiction, then is there anything that is certain at all?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This question had plagued the minds of many great thinkers until a philosopher of equal brilliance reformulated it, much to the dismay of those who wanted to solve Hume&amp;rsquo;s predicament. After several decades of wrestling with problems of perception and observation, Immanuel Kant published his &amp;ldquo;Critique of Pure Reason&amp;rdquo; where he completely redefined our notions of the world and the limitations of reason. Until Kant, it was customary to assume that the world &amp;ldquo;in and of itself&amp;rdquo; was quite similar to the way we perceived it. This assumption conformed with much of daily experience because an object simply doesn&amp;rsquo;t cease to exist just because we don&amp;rsquo;t observe it. When you return home from a long day&amp;rsquo;s work, your home is still there and all the places you had just travelled through to arrive at your home will be there as well. So the realization that our perception of the world at a given moment is limited and that the world which lies outside the bounds of what we can see and hear is similar to the world we perceive seems plausible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However Kant&amp;rsquo;s reflection on the problem of causality led to a radically different conclusion. Despite the fact that Kant agreed with Hume&amp;rsquo;s remark on causality not being logically necessitated by the observation of two subsequent events, causal principles still hold. And they have enabled us to make strides in our understanding of the material world. Therefore what is the origin of causal relationships and by extension of even space and time? Kant&amp;rsquo;s investigation into the nature of these concepts forced him to conclude that the form the world takes for us, a world of objects localized in space and time causing one and another was largely determined by the nature of our sensory apparatus. In his terms, the phenomenal world, the world we perceive and can perceive and which comprised the totality of all possible human knowledge borrowed its fundamental characteristics of space, time and causality from our perceptual apparatus. He completely rejected the notion that the world would remain quite similar to the way we perceived it in the absence of an independent observer. According to Kant, the coherence of the world was something that we had ourselves fashioned, indicative far more of our inability to comprehend without elucidation than the nature of reality itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of this begs the question, if it is our impositions that give continuity to the world of phenomena thereby demarcating a fabric of reality which can be perceived and comprehended, what is the nature of reality devoid of such impositions. This Kant termed as the &amp;ldquo;noumenon&amp;rdquo;, the world in and of itself which by its very nature was unknowable. Kant&amp;rsquo;s conceptualization of the noumenon was widely different from those who came before him. Despite the fact that the noumenon was fundamentally unknowable, he was able to infer its characteristics simply by contrasting it with the phenomenal world. The noumenon knew neither time nor space and in it objects could not cause one another because objects themselves did not exist. The noumenon remains unknowable because concepts of space, time and causality are not merely characteristics of the material world but rather constitute the very preconditions of knowledge itself. Therefore the noumenon did not consist of a plurality of objects abiding by laws of science and logic independent of our perceptions. It was instead a gaping void of sheer mystery that defied all understanding and whose boundaries were visible only in virtue of it being related to a world that we can see and understand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The precise nature of the relationship between the noumenal and the phenomenal, between the world that can be known and its antithesis that will forever elude human knowledge is of profound significance. Kant was able to explain notions of free will and morality by situating individuals at the intersection of both these realms. The individual, he proposed, could initiate actions out of volition and felt compelled to do right by others because a part of his existence was rooted in the noumenon. And it reminded one that whatever difference he observed between mine and thine was only of this world behind which an absolute singularity was always peering through. There were many questions that assailed me when I first encountered these ideas but the most important of them all was why is the noumenon even important?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The blackness I had mentioned initially that confronted me at every juncture of thought and affect could be understood as this unknowable which pervaded all of life. If this blackness was something neither you nor I could escape, why must we even bother ourselves with it? Wouldn&amp;rsquo;t it be insanity to pursue insight into something which at the outset is recognized as an impregnable mystery? Or perhaps there were different ways of understanding that were unfettered by the limitations of thought. Whatever it may be, it seemed fruitless to speculate on the unknowable. Even more so to suggest that it could have any great relevance in the quest of furthering human understanding.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite such reservations, Kant was thoroughly convinced of the importance of the noumenon. Arthur Schopenhauer, a philosopher who greatly contributed and built upon the foundations of Kant&amp;rsquo;s ideas, even vehemently opposed those who entirely rejected its existence and proposed that all of reality can be known. I believe the fundamental conflict which Kant laid bare, atleast for me, is that we were essentially creatures given enough intelligence to know nothing is definitive yet put in a world where we must act definitively. To me the more interesting question was not how we can penetrate this mystery but what must we do in the face of it? Is it even reasonable to talk of &amp;ldquo;musts&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;shoulds&amp;rdquo; when the unknowable threatens to swallow us from all sides?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The sight of the noumenon and any experience of it should leave us paralysed. Paralysed to move, think or even say anything and yet it does not. Accepting Kant for me necessitated embracing the paradox that lied at the heart of the human condition. We can know nothing for certain. All human knowledge can be contradicted. Our judgments of right and wrong, true and false are all mere assumptions. However we are still forced to arrive at conclusions. Some of us appeal to reason while others to faith but regardless of where we go, the noumenon confronts us in all its ambiguity. The word &amp;ldquo;curse&amp;rdquo; appealed to me because at the core of our being there was a dichotomy. An either/or where through thought we can always determine nothing is certain yet must live as though something were. This curse, to me, did not seem like a misunderstanding or an inadequacy from which we could liberate ourseleves through enlightenment. It was rather life itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If I had somehow been right in formulating this paradox, all of human pursuits became equally elusive. I could recognize in some form or the other that all endeavours were essentially a call to the unknown. Art, most of all, reminded us of how ephemeral the distinctions that separated one from the other truly were. And even the distinction that separated one from the world. When enjoying art we feel ourselves to be one with something we seldom understand. And yet those moments are transient. As much as we seek to extinguish the separations between the phenomenal and the noumenal, to glimpse at the unknown even only for a fleeting moment, the &amp;ldquo;I&amp;rdquo; would cease to exist without such separation. Intellectual pursuits, morality and art always reminds us of the fundamental similarities between us but the will to live emphasized the difference. We might feel compassion for our fellow men but we still have to eat and fend for ourselves. It seemed to me that as much as we sought the demise of the &amp;ldquo;I&amp;rdquo; through all these different pursuits we also equally sought its solidification. And life did not consist of escaping this but rather emerged because of it. I know that we might eventually become one with the unknown but for the time, we remain separate from it, forever torn asunder between what we can know and what we should do. Yet despite such a dismal state of affairs, we cannot help but fight the conditions that bring forth life. And perhaps that is all we seek at the end of the day. A good fight.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why Use Linux?</title>
      <link>https://noumenalnotions.space/blogs/why_use_linux/</link>
      <guid>https://noumenalnotions.space/blogs/why_use_linux/</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Mar 2025 21:41:29 IST</pubDate>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-dismal-state-of-affairs&#34;&gt;A Dismal State of Affairs&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The indifference that people show towards technology has always surprised me. By indifference, I do not mean a general lack of interest. It is quite evident that people like to use the latest technology if they ever have the means to and do prefer to invest a lot of time before purchasing any electronic product. However this interest is almost never sustained when it pertains to how technology itself operates. To an end user the only thing that matters if they purchase a smartphone or a laptop is its purpose. If it lets you click a good picture or browse the internet with reasonable efficiency what more is there to know?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The underlying workings of a machine are obviously irrelevant to anyone who intends to simply use them as a means to an end. After all none of us wish to learn the principles of thermodynamics just so that we can drive a car. I think this kind of functional attitude towards technology is prevalent and arises naturally as a response to the increasing complexity of the world. In light of the colossal advancements we have made in the last few decades on several fronts, there is a pressing need to simplify the fruits of human progress. Technology&amp;rsquo;s continued march towards the mastery of our environment is quite useless if it isn&amp;rsquo;t accessible. And what makes it accessible is commonly known as &amp;ldquo;software&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the broadest terms, software represents an attempt to simplify and use the inherent complexity of machines, specifically computers. Any complex machine in order to be used requires a good interface. A link that establishes a connection between the way you want to use it and all the possible ways it can be used. Similar to how a car requires a steering wheel and brakes to be maneuvered properly, computers also require software to utilize its computational power. But unlike cars whose use is limited to transporting a person from one place to another, computers aren&amp;rsquo;t necessarily confined to solving mathematical problems. It could potentially solve any problem given that the problem itself can be translated mathematically and this is precisely what good software intends to do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although most of us are aware of software or more commonly called &amp;ldquo;applications&amp;rdquo; for our day to day use, I think the most essential of all, the beating heart of computers so to speak remains outside common knowledge. And this piece of software is the &amp;ldquo;operating system&amp;rdquo;. The most popular operating system of all, one that everyone uses regularly, has been Windows. Although operating systems as a concept itself isn&amp;rsquo;t that popular, Windows happens to be a part of the vernacular and is associated with the graphical interface you see when you open any newly purchased laptop or computer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For a non technical user, this is where his knowledge ends. He is dimly aware of an entity called Windows that is responsible for producing an overlay he sees every time he opens his personal computer. He goes about his routine perhaps using only a fraction of the functionalities his computer has to offer until he runs into problems. A cryptic error message that usually goes like &amp;ldquo;Something went wrong&amp;rdquo; will often leave him wondering what he did. He might then consider purchasing a new product or seeking the help of a technician whilst revelling in his ignorance of what goes underneath the machine that he uses almost everyday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;is-the-ignorance-tenable&#34;&gt;Is the ignorance tenable?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I had already suggested, it is quite implausible for all of us to know the nitty gritty details of the machines we use. Therefore a certain amount of ignorance is inevitable and perhaps even necessary. However I think computers in the last decade have grown to occupy a unique position in human life that makes the reasons for such ignorance a little more questionable. It is quite evident that computers play a far more integral role in sustaining societal infrastructure than most of our daily appliances. But more importantly, there&amp;rsquo;s no other human invention that has had such a decisive impact in the course of individual life than computers. We have become so reliant on them that our lives are almost intertwined with each other. So it seems to me that any indifference towards their inner workings also amounts to being oblivious to a significant part of our own lives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This might seem like a really long digression from the subject of our discussion. Nonetheless, I think it is indispensable to consider the socio cultural context within which we live in order to have an informed opinion of any aspect of technology. I think it is a grave error to assume that our choice of using a specific application or software does not have deeper cultural implications and this is true specifically for our operating system of choice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the current landscape there are two major choices for operating systems. Windows is one of them and currently dominates the personal desktop market. Most laptops or computers that you might buy is likely to have Windows pre-installed. Windows currently holds a monopoly in personal computing partly due to historical reasons but mostly because of its intuitive GUI. Learning to use it requires no formal pre-requisite as it attempts to mimic our visual experience of reality, deceptively hiding the inner workings of what is being used.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another operating system of stranger origins also presents an equally intriguing choice. Instead of attempting to hide the inner operations of computers, it strives to make it transparent. So transparent that one has unmitigated access to all of the essential files that comprises the core functionalities of the system. The complexity is essentially laid bare in all its glory for the users to behold, leaving the choice of either being daunted or fascinated at the sight of the beating heart to the users themselves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This operating system is prevalently known as &amp;ldquo;Linux&amp;rdquo; or to put it more properly &amp;ldquo;GNU/Linux&amp;rdquo;. The history of the Linux operating system and how it came about is quite elaborate and constitutes a significant part of the history of personal computing. I think an average user would find most of it irrelevant and rightly so since it has no immediate bearing to the continued functioning of the devices he uses. A question he would find more pertinent is &amp;ldquo;What exactly does Linux has to offer that Windows cannot?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-linux&#34;&gt;Why Linux?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the very outset, Linux might seem superior to Windows due to its architectural differences and undoubtedly this might be its biggest advantage. Given its modular approach towards computing, Linux is far more efficient in the way it functions compared to Windows which is monolithic by design. In addition to this, Linux also affords extreme customization and flexibility to users, a variety of GUI interfaces and the freedom to modify and distribute its code which makes Linux free and open source. Due to the technical reasons mentioned and many more, Linux dominates almost every operating system market with the exception of personal computers. But it is also true that most of these advantages, although significant enough for someone to consider switching to Linux, still might not entirely be relevant to a user who simply wants to expedite his work. So notwithstanding these technicalities, what more is there?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my opinion, the most rewarding part of using Linux is not related to its technical superiority. All of the aforementioned advantages that Linux offers clearly improves user experience in substantial ways but the actual benefits of using it lies in its approach and philosophy towards computing. I had mentioned that how indifferent people were towards technology always surprised me because it essentially amounted to being indifferent to a significant part of one&amp;rsquo;s own life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The philosophy of Linux views this indifference as detrimental and perhaps even down right decadent because it divorces the user from a machine he increasingly relies on for his daily functioning. This does not mean that Linux comes with an inscrutable interface that you will have to spend years learning in order to use it properly. Many Linux distributions come with a GUI that is quite intuitive but it still affords the possibility of dwelling deeper into the system. Linux at its very heart is a kind of system that engenders exploration and curiosity about itself and this difference is what sets it miles apart from Windows. Such an attitude and respect it holds for its users also partly eliminates the possibility of capitalizing on the ignorance towards a particular system. Users can either rest content with what they are presented by the interface or dive deeper, trying to understand how all of the intricate components come together as one seamless visual experience he beholds everyday. I think Linux makes evident the kind of sheer wizardry that is involved in making computers work and transforms any menial task you might do on a regular basis as an adventure of its own.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So for both technical and non technical users alike, Linux seems like an extremely intriguing choice for the reasons considered. Given the fact that a user overcomes his reluctance to entirely switch to a different operating system on the whim that the grass might be greener on the other side, I believe he would be rarely disappointed because it is.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>An Either/Or</title>
      <link>https://noumenalnotions.space/essays/an_either_or/</link>
      <guid>https://noumenalnotions.space/essays/an_either_or/</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Feb 2025 22:13:59 IST</pubDate>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I have been preoccupied with a morbid thought ever since I began writing about the limitations of human language. The fact that language sometimes falls shorts in expressing what we think and feel is by no means a novel idea. Philosophers, immemorially, have debated on the nature of human language and perhaps ironically have attempted to demonstrate through words how inadequate they can be. This realization is quite frightening, partly because it implies that regardless of how clearly or brilliantly we endeavour to express ourselves, the essential substance of our experience will remain within us, forever inaccessible to anyone outside our physical self.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However behind this peculiar idea, something even stranger was peering through. I have always conceived words and perhaps even thought itself to be categorical in nature. Words, to me, are a vessel of thought and through its utterance we differentiate human experience. By ascribing symbols to objects and communicating those symbols with each other, we attempt to share our experiences hoping atleast tentatively to bridge the gulf that separates one individual from another. But the purpose of words and as an extension of thought itself is to grasp something for what it is in its &amp;ldquo;totality&amp;rdquo;. We do not rest content with symbols themselves but through them always try to portray and infer the objects they represent. Through differentiation, we want to find that which is being differentiated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This relationship between words and things also seemed to belie the relationship between form and substance. Any work of literature, art or music harboured this essential quality of trying to grasp substance devoid of form. Through words, we try to negate language. Through music we try to transcend sound. Through art we try to push the boundaries of space and time. Every human endeavour is a constant striving to negate form through form. However, the laws of perception dictate the impossibility of apprehending such a formless entity. And besides, differentiation is also the essential condition of human existence. Without form, substance is merely a seething mass of nothingness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It seemed to me that all of human activity was essentially an attempt to undo the evolutionary gift of consciousness to strive towards this nothingness. We are clearly separate from each other but there is something in us that yearns to be one. That yearns to return to the oblivion from which it sprang. That yearns to remember life before remembering. Such an inexplicable yearning which peered through all human endeavours makes life now for me all the more frightening.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Inconsistencies of Language</title>
      <link>https://noumenalnotions.space/essays/the_inconsistencies_of_language/</link>
      <guid>https://noumenalnotions.space/essays/the_inconsistencies_of_language/</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Jan 2025 22:14:00 IST</pubDate>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Language initially enters the purview of human experience as an instrument of communication. As toddlers, we experience the world around us while having very little means at our disposal to communicate the former. Any kind of articulation at that stage is often monosyllabic where the recipients of our incoherent babbles make all the effort to understand our intentions. Language in such a primitive form proves to be of little value because the need to understand is seldom matched by a clarity in expression. Although one could still derive meaning from them by either accounting for non verbal cues or placing words in their context, language still remains predominantly unilateral.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Without the aid of any formal training whatsoever, our use of language evolves from a mere expression of fundamental desires into a vessel for thought. Thought and language develop almost synonymously, each complementing and reinforcing the growth of the other. We become capable of comprehending complex symbolism and abstractions. Find ourselves correlating the meaning of fictional narratives to real life. We are, in a sense, transformed as the seed of language grows to its fruition, furnishing us with ever new means to not only express what we think and feel but also to peer into the minds of others who deign to do the same.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As much as language attempts to bridge the chasm that separates human experience, it still remains far from obvious if it sometimes does not also have the opposite effect. It seems to me that like any human invention, the utility of an object is partly determined by the manner in which we employ it. So it naturally follows that the utility of language must also be determined by those who can either seek to demystify or elude that which is already obscure. But sometimes we encounter individuals who demonstrate an almost uncanny ability to comprehend what we think and feel, even if our experience is deliberately veiled in abtruse wordings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There also others who, despite our most ardent efforts to articulate precisely, fail to grasp even the most elementary meanings of what we say, let alone understand our hopes and wishes. In such instances, we often say that that the person speaks or rather fails to speak &amp;ldquo;our language&amp;rdquo;. So ultimately language appears to be an affair that exists, not in isolation, but in this nebulous sphere of contact that is brought about by the meeting of two individuals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If this were to be true, in addition to the plethora of dialects and semantics that superficially demarcate one language from another, there also seems to be encapsulations that develop within a specific language itself. Encapsulations that arise as a result of communication with an individual for a sustained period of time. Within this tenuous fabric, words acquire meanings and connotations that might either agree or altogether contradict that of the vernacular. Nonetheless despite such similarities or differences, for those within the fabric words always mean the same. But they also mean more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is quite apparent that there is an element of beauty to this. The fact that language not only facilitates the mere expression of ideas but can also be employed as a medium through which people can often mean more than what they say is clearly a testament to human ingenuity. Writers, after all, find themselves constantly pushing and redefining the boundaries of their own fabric to be able to convey to everyone something only they seem to understand. However for those of us who neither have the time nor the talent to maneuver through the traps of human lexicon, our boundaries tend to exclude far more than it accommodates. Such exclusion seems like a natural consequence of forming human relationships. Or perhaps of even simply being different from another person. If so, is it an exclusion that we must necessarily strive to eliminate?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So underneath these obvious connections that language helps forge between people, there exists a primordial tension where being understood is constantly negated by the very medium that occasions understanding. The moment one articulates anything by giving it shape and form, a part of its meaning becomes incommunicable and remains forever within the confines of our own experience. Although the clear existence of gradations in understanding places an individual closer or distant from oneself, the essential part of any human experience is still a fundamental assertion of our abject loneliness. Therefore the more one has to say, one realizes that words often fail in adequately expressing anything of great concern, even when it comes to our most intimate acquaintance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not only do we tend to exclude those who do not share the layered meanings we ascribe to words and things, even with those who do share them the struggle to fully express one&amp;rsquo;s being is ever present and perhaps becomes even more pressing as that struggle constantly seeks to extinguish the very separation that defines a person. I believe the problem of language fundamentally rests in this fact, that how can one possibly say something that is of profound personal significance to anyone without losing oneself where every word that is uttered becomes a proclamation of both our identity and difference from each other. Isn&amp;rsquo;t the separation that divides individuals also the separation that defines us? Must we not entirely lose ourselves to be understood?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to set up weechat relay</title>
      <link>https://noumenalnotions.space/blogs/weechat_relay/</link>
      <guid>https://noumenalnotions.space/blogs/weechat_relay/</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Oct 2024 09:01:16 IST</pubDate>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;So weechat is one among many clients that is used to connect to an irc network. Unlike other messaging platforms where you recieve a message that was sent to you even if you are not online, IRC functions in way that requires your client to constantly stay connected to the server to recieve messages. So if your user disconnects, you won&amp;rsquo;t be able to receive messages nor will you be able to access past messages that you sent in a particular channel. To circuvment this users often employ an irc bouncer like znc or soju that stays connected to an irc network and &amp;ldquo;bounces off&amp;rdquo; the messages it recieves when you connect to it using a client. Weechat affords its own kind of bouncer which is called a relay which provides similar functionalities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to set up a weechat relay, you first require a server that has weechat installed. You can create an account in any tilde community if you require a free shell account. Once you have access to a server, you simply open weechat and add the servers you would like to connect to. For instance if you would like to connect to libera:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;/server add libera irc.libera.chat/6697 -tls&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After adding a server you can sometimes directly connect to it by executing:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;/connect libera&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, if Libera requires your server to authenticate via SASL you would need to set the sasl username and password using the following commands:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;/set irc.server.libera.sasl_username &amp;quot;mynick&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;/set irc.server.libera.sasl_password &amp;quot;password&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;SASL is a method through which a user can register their nick and password on a particular IRC network so if they perchance disconnect, they can still assume their nickname by sending the password they used to register the nick to NickServ in Libera. Users can message other users or bots using:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;/query NickServ or /query any_use&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This will open a query window and if the user types help once they start a query with NickServ, they will be greeted with a list of commands they can use to register their nicknames.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After a successful connection to a server, the user can start setting up the weechat relay using the following commands:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;/relay add ssl.irc 700&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This creates a relay in our specificed port. It is usually recommended to use a port range that higher and unspecified.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;/secure set relay PASSWOR&lt;/code&gt;
&lt;code&gt;/set relay.network.password &amp;quot;PASSWORD&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So far, the commands we have executed on the server side instance of weechat has established a connection to an irc network and set up a relay. After executing a &amp;ldquo;/save&amp;rdquo;, the user can exit weechat and then generate an ssl certificate. SSL or its predecessor TLS, is a mechanism through which two clients establish end to end encryption. The protocol usually sits between the HTTP and TCP layer and facilitates most kinds of encrypted connections. In order for our client to securely connect to the relay in our server, we are required to generate a self signed certificate. In order to do that the user should cd into the weechat config directory which most likely would be &amp;ldquo;~/.config/weechat/&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Depending on the weechat version, they should either create an &amp;ldquo;ssl&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;tls&amp;rdquo; directory within the config path and then generate a certificate with the name &amp;ldquo;relay.pem&amp;rdquo;. (Older versions of weechat use the term &amp;ldquo;tls&amp;rdquo;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;export HOSTNAME=example.org
openssl req -x509 -nodes -newkey rsa:2048 -keyout relay.pem -extensions san_env \
  -subj &amp;#34;/O=WeeChat/CN=$HOSTNAME&amp;#34; \
  -config &amp;lt;(cat /etc/ssl/openssl.cnf &amp;lt;(printf &amp;#34;\n[ san_env ]\nsubjectAltName=DNS:\${ENV::HOSTNAME}&amp;#34;)) \
  -days 365 -out relay.pem
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;If the server does not have a hostname, a certificate with jus the ip can also be generated&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;export IP=192.168.1.2
openssl req -x509 -nodes -newkey rsa:2048 -keyout relay.pem \
  -subj &amp;#34;/O=weechat/CN=my-weechat&amp;#34; \
  -config &amp;lt;(cat /etc/ssl/openssl.cnf &amp;lt;(printf &amp;#34;\n[v3_ca]\nsubjectAltName = @alternate_names\n[alternate_names]\nIP.1 = \${ENV::IP}&amp;#34;)) \
   -days 365 -out relay.pem
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;Once the certificate has been generated, the certificate can be loaded on to weechat by opening weechat and executing:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;/relay sslcertke&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Afer this, the user can connect to the relay using any client which includes weechat as well. If the user chooses weechat as the client, then once again we are required to add a server using the /server command but this time we use the ip of our server where the weechat relay is running instead of the irc network.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;/server add libera ip_of_host/port_number -ssl -autoconnect&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The user can also use a hostname of the server if it has a registered domain. After this the user can configure the local client to use a password to connect to the relay using:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;/secure set relay PASSWORD (same as the one used on the server&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before connecting to the relay, we are also required to set a password for the server using:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;/set irc.server.libera.password &amp;quot;libera:PASSWORD&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &amp;ldquo;libera&amp;rdquo; prefix before the password tells the relay which network we would like to connect to. We can simply add more networks on the server side by following the same steps and then modify the password according to the name of our network on the client.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most often, the server side time does not align with the time zone the client is connecting from. In order to display the time correctly we can set the option:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;/set irc.server_default.capabilities &amp;quot;server-time&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The final step is to ensure that the weechat on the client side accepts the certificate that the server provides. Most likely this will not be the default behaviour because the weechat client does not accept self signed certificate. In order to configure this we simply set:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;/set weechat.network.gnutls_ca_user &amp;quot;path_to_certificate&amp;quot;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This particular option should point to a local copy of certificate we generated on the server side. We can also toggle the &amp;ldquo;tls_verify&amp;rdquo; or the &amp;ldquo;ssl_verify&amp;rdquo; option for the particular network but that would invariably ignore the verification of all certificates. Once this is done the client should be able to connect to the weechat relay and join channels.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Musings About the Devil</title>
      <link>https://noumenalnotions.space/blogs/musings_about_the_devil/</link>
      <guid>https://noumenalnotions.space/blogs/musings_about_the_devil/</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 May 2024 09:02:32 IST</pubDate>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The world of today is not particularly concerned of antiquated ideas like angels or demons. From the contemporary point of view, anything that does not retain an objective existence which can be proved by methods of science are simply dismissed as the whims of human imagination. Such a frame of reference has always struck me as sensible because it grounds individuals on a plane of existence which, they know for a fact, to be true. However, I have also been exposed to a plethora of modern ideas, one of which is the notion of trauma.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being a student of psychology, I have spent quite some time trying to understand the various ways trauma confines and hinders the will of an individual. Psychological literature records an array of illnesses ranging from anxiety disorders to OCD where the mind of a person is in constant battle with certain thoughts and ideas originating from within. Notwithstanding the fact that such illnesses merit proper treatment, I couldn&amp;rsquo;t help but noticing that there was often a tendency to associate the illness with the person itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I believe the cardinal difference between tragedy and trauma is that eventhough both of those words represent external occurings, in the former the individual is still separate from the tragedy. Although he might might not able to control the circumstances around him, he is still in full possession of his inner faculties whereas with the latter, suffering becomes internalized and dictates his course of action. Trauma, therefore through a process of internalization, becomes a part of the person itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In light of these reflections, I understood that these modern notions as much as they shed clarity in certain respects also raise some fundamental questions. And that these seemingly antiquated ideas, like the devil, also served a unique purpose. Initially, I used to abhor this prevalent convention of blaming all the evils of the world on the devil because it clearly absolved the person of moral responsibility. Simply projecting all your decadence and wickedness to a mythical figure seemed deterimental at the outset because it might most often serve as an excuse to remain oblivious to the consequences of your own actions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However if the devil is the origin of all wrongdoing, the will of the person is also in a certain way protected,. As much as such externalization might lead a person to assume they are not responsible for their own actions, it also ensures that any immorality is not intertwined with a person because the source of all evil is external. The individual is armed with a mechanism that allows him to choose his way, regardless of his past. Perhaps modern psychology still has much to learn from such ideas that are often dismissed under the pretext of being naive superstition.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Quest for Normalcy</title>
      <link>https://noumenalnotions.space/essays/quest_for_normalcy/</link>
      <guid>https://noumenalnotions.space/essays/quest_for_normalcy/</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 Mar 2024 22:14:00 IST</pubDate>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;With each passing day, I find myself increasingly confronted with valid reasons as to why psychology is an essentially doomed enterprise. It is evidently quite paradoxical for a student of psychology to feel this way but what perplexes me even more is why such a question does not often arise in the minds of individuals who pursue this discipline. Unlike other endeavours whose object of study lends itself very well to empirical scrutiny, psychological inquiry attempts to categorize something which, by its very nature, resists definition. The workings of our mind are always veiled by our inclination towards self analysis, and only reveals itself in its disintegration. This is perhaps why the phenomenon of mental illness has informed much of our knowledge regarding the psyche because pathology allows us to investigate the dark recesses of the human mind which is always concealed in its functional counterpart.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Freud, for instance, conceived an entire theory of personality through his attempt to cure patients afflicted with hysteria. His investigation into the various psychological afflictions of his clientele created an opportunity where he could peer through the pretense of our modern tastes and sensibilities only to find that the mind was still under the sway of primordial instincts. Notwithstanding the insights such analysis has furnished whose influence is perhaps yet to be determined, it still suffers from a grave misconception. The reason a significant part of Freud&amp;rsquo;s understanding is now subject to disagreement is because his theoretical premise is derived from an investigation of pathology. A pathological mind, as much as it reveals all that which was formerly inexplicable, also distorts our perception of the very mechanism it renders evident.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although we have come to liberate ourselves from some of Freud&amp;rsquo;s antiquated ideas, we are still trapped in his old habits. Much like Freud, we still try to understand the psyche and what is &amp;rsquo;normal&amp;rsquo; by investigating what is dysfunctional. I believe introducing the word &amp;rsquo;normal&amp;rsquo; here is by no means a sleight of hand because any inquiry into the human mind is premised upon the inclination to discover some organizing principle which enables us to understand and predict human behaviour. The form of this principle might manifest differently in the lives of individuals but its essence must remain the same. The discovery of this principle, I believe, constitutes the fundamental task of psychology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, unlike other disciplines, psychology is mired in the paradox that an individual by definition is an outlier. A person is almost infinitely different in the way he thinks and behaves compared to others. He harbours a myriad of hopes and dreams and is laden with as many personal inadequacies. Such a vagary among individuals obviously makes the task of establishing a true normal utterly impossible because to what standard must the individual be even compared to? Social norms and morals are often a product of their time and could not possibly meet the ever changing circumstances in the life of an individual. Therefore it seems quite reasonable to assume that there are infinite ways to be as long as that way of life does not produce any dysfunction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Such a negative definition of normalcy, although plausible, still fails to address certain fundamental questions. What is the ultimate purpose of the mind&amp;rsquo;s habitual activity of assimilation and understanding? From where does its relentless need to question, ponder, create and reflect originate? Although tracing the endless chain of causes and effects in explaining behaviour might provide some semblance of understanding, we are still willfully blind if we choose to ignore the simple question of where such causes and effects ultimately tend towards.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the cardinal reasons for the infamous rift between Freud and his most prized disciple, C.G Jung rested on this disagreement. Where Freud stayed content with trying to understand the mind by investigating its antecedent psychological causes, Jung saw the obvious limitation of constricting the psyche to a merely reactionary organism. Jung believed that the psyche was as much constructive as it was reactive in nature and discovered that its inner workings often betrayed the existence of an obscure ideal around which all psychological processes revolved. An obscure ideal, which he termed the Self, that not only subordinated all psychological activity but also weaved together the vagaries of living such activity invariably produced.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;None of the aforementioned deliberations suggest the imposition of a particular way of living. Psychological inquiry is often too consumed in navigating the labyrinth of causes and effects that it blatantly refuses to acknowledge that there must be some ideal or principle which gives direction to the sheer breadth of mental functioning. Since the existence of such a principle often calls for ways of thinking which push the boundaries of scientific rigour, we rest content with the assumption that normalcy simply refers to an absence of dysfunction. The desire to arrive at such a conclusion and the reluctance to part from it could be ascribed to the misconception that normalcy, in this context, can only be defined in comparison to the majority. However, the true normal of psychology neither lies in the deafening voice of the majority nor in the eccentric opinions of the minority. It instead lies in that very principle which informs much of what we think and feel. A principle which, instead of defining what is normal through morbidity, evinces what it means to truly live.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Correspondent Inference</title>
      <link>https://noumenalnotions.space/blogs/correspondent_inference/</link>
      <guid>https://noumenalnotions.space/blogs/correspondent_inference/</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Feb 2024 09:02:14 IST</pubDate>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;Hell is other people&amp;rdquo; - Sartre&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have recently been thinking a fair bit about something called correspondent inference. It is essentially a concept in psychology that represents our proclivity to presume that a person&amp;rsquo;s overt behaviour represents stable personality traits. Although initially learning the concept didn&amp;rsquo;t precipitate any kind of reflection, I seem to have suddenly become aware of how often we do that to each other and perhaps even to ourselves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Attempts at coming to grips with my social reality has been mired with fateful detours. Regardless of how much I have struggled with trying to understand the intricacies involved in social interactions, it has become increasingly clear to me that people require some conception of whoever they interact with. Conceptions they either form at first sight or through sustained conversations. But the need to reduce the person to some finite understanding is ever present in all facets of discourse. It appears to me that more than just serving an operating principle that guides behaviour such conceptions become dogma which we tenaciously cling to make sense of others. Dogma without which the social fabric becomes filled with individuals whose existence defies coherence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wouldn&amp;rsquo;t have imagined that Sartre&amp;rsquo;s most quoted maxim &amp;ldquo;Hell is other people&amp;rdquo; would be echoed within the confines of my own life. For what makes others Hell is precisely this need to reduce the idiosyncrasy of an individual into something finite and comprehensible by thought. But an individual&amp;rsquo;s essence, if we can speculate upon that, transcends the realm of coherence and thought does it not? Does a person cease to exist or does he commit a grave error against himself if his actions sometimes go against his usually &amp;ldquo;expected&amp;rdquo; behaviour? What exactly constitutes the individual?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I find myself returning to these questions whose answers, it is clear, that I must labour for. But what is evident to me at least is that one can never truly know someone by what they say or what they do. Such markers at best indicate the nexus from which the former springs. Words and actions only serve as a means to understand but not conclude of the ineffable mystery that lies underneath the semblance we perceive.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Thoughts on Normalcy</title>
      <link>https://noumenalnotions.space/blogs/thoughts_on_normalcy/</link>
      <guid>https://noumenalnotions.space/blogs/thoughts_on_normalcy/</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Feb 2024 09:02:22 IST</pubDate>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;With each passing day, I find myself confronted with increasingly valid reasons as to why psychology is a doomed enterprise. It is evidently quite paradoxical for a student of psychology to feel this way but what perplexes me even more is why such reasons generally do not foster thoughtful deliberation. One question that has recently occupied my mind pertains to the task of establishing normalcy within psychology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It appears to me that, normalcy in the hard sciences is relatively simple to determine. For instance with the case of polydactyly which refers to the condition of having more than five fingers, it only takes mere comparison to understand why that particular condition is pathological. Since the majority of the population only have five fingers any deviations from that norm becomes abnormal. In line with simple observation, pathology seems to correspond to the degree to which a condition varies from the mean of the population.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, this convention holds very little water in a psychological context because an individual, by definition, is a deviation from the norm. Consequently any study of individuals must adopt a different approach to establish normalcy within its discipline and this is where its inquiry becomes increasingly obscure. Psychological theories that I have hitherto studied implicitly come to define what is normal in an attempt to understand mind and behaviour. Freud&amp;rsquo;s theories on psychosexual development even explicitly state that any arrest in the stages of development would occasion personalities that could be deemed as pathological. However I believe such theories still suffer from the dearth of a higher ideal which is often what provides clarity in any investigation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the study of medicine, it is fairly obvious that the mechanisms of the body operate collectively to ensure the survival of the organism. Although there might be a few instances where our physiology appears to work at cross purposes with that objective, it is still the general direction that it tends towards. However what is the purpose of the mind? Why does the psyche engage in its habitual activity of assimilation and understanding? It seems that psychological inquiry has only resorted to sidestepping the question of &amp;ldquo;normalcy&amp;rdquo; by merely looking at the mind in functional terms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although tenable, this line of investigation is bound to suffer from the limitation that there are an infinite ways to be as long as the individual is able to function. Such negative definitions only serve to disguise an alarming problem which now confronts psychological endeavours. That how can one define normal without taking recourse to pathology. If psychology ever wishes to escape the labyrinth of subjectivity, it must liberate itself from the perspective of illnesses and embark on the obscure endeavour of seeking the higher ideal which subordinates the psyche. The study of that ideal, I believe, is essential if we hope to free ourselves of the illusion that any manner of being that does not produce dysfunction is representative of normalcy.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Vinland Saga: Breaking Free from Causality</title>
      <link>https://noumenalnotions.space/essays/vinland_saga/</link>
      <guid>https://noumenalnotions.space/essays/vinland_saga/</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 Jan 2024 22:14:01 IST</pubDate>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It is always difficult to articulate why it is that a work of art leaves a lasting impression on those who witness it. Although you can try to explain such an abiding influence by deconstructing its various elements some of which in this case happens to be the extremely well woven characters, the handling of the complex dynamic between them, the amount of precision dedicated towards their history and most importantly the breathtaking story we see unfold between a son and a father. Vinland Saga is definitely impressive for all these reasons but I believe there comes a point where it becomes more than just a cocktail of greatness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The narrative, as it unravels, places Thorfinn amidst an especially violent setting. Being the son of a great warrior and raised in the throes of consuming revenge alongside his fathers murderer, Thorfinn spends most of his formative years learning how to kill. His unwavering persistence in avenging his father is at the center of a metamorphosis which transforms Thorfinn from a naive curious little kid whose eyes gleam with awe and wonder into a bloodthirsty creature lusting for vengeance. As much as it is heartbreaking to see Thorfinn become all that his father did not want him to be, it paradoxically also forms the prerequisite for understanding a rather cryptic sentence You have no enemies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a sense, Vinland Saga could be described as simply a rumination of what this statement truly means. A rumination that portrays the initial disbelief for such words, its seeming irrationality, the subsequent violence that ensues and finally the ineffable wisdom that lay underneath it. Initially the story only seems to be culminating towards a point where Thorfinn eventually exacts his cathartic revenge on Askeladd, his fathers murderer. But soon after he dies, things begin to change. Thorfinn is left aimless and his hopes of avenging his father now forever beyond his grasp. Neither having any purpose to live nor a reason to die, Thorfinn finds himself laboring in a farm where he meets Einar whose friendship helps him confront the demons he buried. Demons who take the form of those he had slayed in his quest for vengeance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thorfinn is a character who is given every possible justification to be violent. He is an exceptionally skilled warrior and is singularly determined when it comes to combat. He lost his father to a band of mercenaries when he was young and spent most of his life filled with resentment. Here is a man who has endured untold suffering in his life and is perhaps rightly justified in regarding those around him as his enemies. And yet how could he not have any enemies?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The cycle of violence that we observe in Vinland Saga has one curious element to it. Everyone has a reason to kill. Some kill for sustenance. Some for glory. Others because they have simply been raised as warriors and cannot envision another manner of living. Violence is shown as being a part and parcel of human nature. An inevitable consequence for any person who wants to protect himself or his family. In such a world, renouncing violence would be a sign of brazen stupidity, tantamounting even to death. But perhaps it might also ultimately be our path to salvation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I believe what sets apart Vinland Saga is that it doesnt settle for the conventional narrative of good and evil where good eventually triumphs. It cuts through the heart of the problem by weaving a story which not only shows the reasons behind the decadence of human beings but also the strength of their will to break out of it. It seems to me that the statement You have no enemies does not represent a factual claim. There are certainly many things out there in the world that seek to hurt and kill, the worst of which as Vinland Saga shows, are members of our own kind. What it does represent instead is an act of faith which stems from a belief in the fundamental virtue of human nature. An act of faith which also emerges from an understanding that regardless of how much we consider ourselves to be fettered by circumstance, we can still break free from it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this way Thorfinn appears to be markedly different from the others characters because he is able to set himself free from this cycle of violence by embodying a certain kind of value. A value which, although could be explicitly formulated as representing &amp;ldquo;empathy&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;self sacrifice&amp;rdquo;, encapsulates a notion that runs far deeper. From a historical point of view, Thorfinn as a character could be compared to Christ because the idea of self sacrifice, in a sense, is at the core of both of these individuals. Much like how Christ had died for the sins of all mankind, Thorfinn exclaims that he has no enemies and responds to violent blows and insults hurled towards him with unmitigated compassion. As much as such an act of faith moves us, it still becomes thoroughly nonsensical once we attempt to understand it. Why must we cultivate empathy and compassion for those who seek to harm us?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As admirable as these values may be, they seem to fly in the face of reason and runs contrary to the pragmatism that informs much of how we behave. Nonetheless even pragmatism proves to be unreliable in certain situations. Situations where every choice you are presented with appears equally wrong. Regardless of how much we employ reason to maneuver through them, they remain inscrutable and force us to be a cog in a long chain of causal events that neither has a beginning nor an end. Much like those vikings of Vinland Saga born into a world of violence and bloodshed, we come to accept the reality that is presented to us. Under the pretense of acceptance and adaptation, we justify perpetuating a cycle of depravity in however small form because it always seems to be the most logical thing to do. And yet Thorfinn transcends this perfectly rational cycle of never ending violence through a feat of irrationality. By embodying the principle of self sacrifice he loses himself to the world. But paradoxically, it is also that very act which redeems him from his decadent past.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Observing this, it is quite evident that the more we ponder on the nature of these values and principles, the more they elude our understanding. Although we might comprehend how these values are justified in specific contexts, we are still left bewildered with their purpose as an overarching principle that guides our way of living. However, the significance of such values does not merely lie in its utility as a guiding principle. Thorfinn&amp;rsquo;s attempt to break free from a vicious cycle of violence despite his cynical past comes not simply from a place of conviction but also from a place of freedom.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being compassionate to those who seek to harm you. Voluntarily accepting the suffering of other&amp;rsquo;s as one&amp;rsquo;s own fundamentally represent acts of freedom. Freedom from the shackles of causality that reduce individuals to machines that simply react. When you take this into account, the seeming irrationality of values like &amp;ldquo;self sacrifice&amp;rdquo; in most situations appears incidental because any act of freedom in a world where choices are made for consequences is bound to seem thoroughly stupid. However, when the space between a choice and its consequence begins to widen. When a decision is made simply for the sake of itself and nothing else. It is in only those rare moments that we see a glimpse of human greatness.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Religious Ruminations</title>
      <link>https://noumenalnotions.space/essays/religious_ruminations/</link>
      <guid>https://noumenalnotions.space/essays/religious_ruminations/</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Dec 2022 22:14:00 IST</pubDate>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Any preoccupation with the religious understanding of our time will often lead one to conclude that efforts directed towards its appraisal is much well spent in more lucrative endeavors. This instant disenchantment occasioned by the pragmatic outlook of modernity has caused a lot of individuals to drift away from value systems of the past and has prompted them to strike new paths in hopes of creating their own meaning in life. But on theother hand there also those who find contemporary times to be shallow and superficial in its attempt to offer purpose and resort to religious values of antiquity hoping to find what they had somehow lost in the course of their secular development. Both of these extremes are accompanied by their own tribulations and the polarizing rhetoric of our time appears to have widened the chasm that already exists between them. The former ascribing precedence to the autonomy of the human will while the latter in its predominant mode of expression seeking to subjugate volition through the postulation of divine providence. Both of these Weltanschauung has come to characterize contemporary religious and political discourse, vying to prove that the other side of the aisle is not only oblivious to the havoc wreaked by its ideological frame of reference but also willfully blind to the stultification of its exponents. I shall perhaps try to examine what motivations predisposes one to reject either of these alternatives and also in rare cases try to reconcile them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a child I had spent most of my formative years in the auspices of a religious school which, although seemingly aspired to engender critical thought, had been overly stringent in its attempt to ensure that none of us were exposed to perspectives that would prompt one to question the theological foundations of our religion. It was assumed to be proven beyond a shadow of doubt that not only do these values represent God&amp;rsquo;s will and his supreme guidance bestowed upon mankind but also that our understanding of them were inerrant and in need of no reform. Perhaps they had thought it was prudent to shield us from predicaments which would have precipitated a crisis in faith given our feeble convictions but only at the expense of ruthlessly suppressing all forms of dissent from the religious status quo. I had come to notice that any kind responsibility they had felt to foster a genuine motivation to discover the truth was triumphed by an unswerving fidelity to defend their religion against external censure. The values they had sought to defend notwithstanding the immense scope and magnitude of their wisdom somehow in the process of their dogmatization had come to exercise a rather stultifying influence on those who believed in them. But is it reasonable to ascribe this influence to the values themselves?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ruminating on the ill effects of dogmatic certainty and the extent to which if at all the underlying religious ideas had contributed to the former, I came to realize the story of the fall of Lucifer increasingly seemed like a prescient warning. Different religions of the Abrahamic corpus contain slight variations of the story but the central theme more or less remains the same, that the devil being a creature ensconced in the highest state of grace and exaltation was cast out of heaven because he dared to question God at the expense of his own fealty. Although the devil in some sense personifies the spirit of intellect, what particularly characterizes him is that his intellect is incapable of acknowledging its own limits. Lucifer regarded himself to be the ultimate arbiter of divine truth so his sin it seemed to me is not only that of pride but also of certainty. What constituted his evil mode of being was that he was a creature bereft of doubt. Reducing Lucifer&amp;rsquo;s cardinal sin partly to a lack of skepticism appeared to have staggering implications in the realm of religious discourse for it presents an almost insurmountable difficulty with faith in the sacred. How exactly is one supposed to have faith without falling into the sin of excessive pride and crippling intransigence? Doesn&amp;rsquo;t faith necessarily entail an eradication of doubt as to matters of religion or does it perhaps indicate a state of human existence that is far more mysterious than what we usually presume?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although it seems reasonable to assume that faith in a higher power would invariably instill humility and compassion, my experience indicated that more often than not it was also accompanied by an unassailable confidence in one&amp;rsquo;s own aptitude to comprehend that power. I seemed to realize that notwithstanding the piety and discipline of all those who espouse allegiance to a divine being, they also come to tacitly regard themselves as capable of understanding the mysterious ways of an entity which by its very nature must remain ineffable and beyond human comprehension. I struggled to understand if faith in divine providence necessarily entailed faith in one specific interpretation of that providence. If so wouldn&amp;rsquo;t that lead to the same mortal error which the devil had committed all those aeons ago that occasioned the dawn of humanity? If not what is the true nature of faith? The more I deliberated on the nature of these questions, the more it became evident to me that faith was far from sheer certainty in the absence of reason. What particularly characterizes the seemingly pious individuals of our time most of who have dedicated their entire lives to articulating their religious paradigms is that instead of worshipping and submitting themselves to a God that existed outside the narrow confines of our feeble intelligence they instead come to worship an idea of God conceived by that very intelligence. Their adherence to a specific scripture and the belief in the perennial values contained therein renders them susceptible to the same primordial sin which the devil had once committed against God. It leads them to think, just like the devil once had, that their understanding of divine reality and of all its intricacies reflected reality per se, precluding any form of knowledge that might exist outside their constricted wisdom.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is woefully ironic to recognize that the clutches of the devil become ever more gripping as one strives to walk the path of God and making such an association in the first place might even seem like a callous sleight of hand. But this ineptitude to detach the understanding of divinity with the divinity itself in my opinion produces an unbelievable inflation of one&amp;rsquo;s intelligence that invariably leads to an uncompromising tenacity which at times might even border on religious fanaticism. Faith in such instances becomes distorted into sheer ruthless convi tion as to the verity of one&amp;rsquo;s beliefs, making way for the manifestation of nefarious impulses under the pretext of furthering the will of God.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, a complete renunciation of religious values and of faith in their general validity is said to plunge an individual into the abysmal depths of moral chaos where the autonomy of the human will is no longer subordinated to the mystery of transcendence. The individual is liberated from the metaphysical systems of the past which prompts to act in a manner that is no longer constrained by the moral restrictions that had once governed his mode of conduct. Although it would be unreasonable to claim that a person who has forsaken religion or at the least finds it highly implausible finds himself divorced from ethical obligations, the metaphysical underpinnings that had once supported moral values in his eyes cease to be tenable. Consequently, the rationale behind traditions of antiquity is brought into diligent scrutiny while the subjects that had hitherto been shunned in human discourse due to their sacrosanct nature is resuscitated with a newfound vigour and discussed in the hopes of furthering the spirit of critical inquiry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Notwithstanding the astute insights such discussions might furnish if they are brought into the forefront of human discourse, the values in question are also exposed to unwarranted criticisms because of their rationally inexplicable nature. The general attitude fostered by the Enlightenment renders not only the existence of angels and demons to be astronomically improbable but more importantly considers faith itself in the absence of evidence to be a precarious venture reserved only for those of the past who were unfortunately not graced with our incredulity. This skepticism for the most part informed the spirit of the Enlightenment, inspiring thinkers of that time to seek a means of apprehending reality that was more rational and objective. Although this epistemological method has immensely furthered our ability to represent what we generally describe as the objective world, it has also profoundly undermined the notion of having faith in absence of reason. The dogmatic subservience which was once regarded as a sign of piety now became an impediment to the progress of true knowledge. The individual refuses to be dissuaded by metaphysical exhortations in his pursuit of truth and seeks the stock of experience while accepting the tribulations such a path might entail. Faith, in such a context, is construed as being positively detrimental to any scholastic enterprise for it demands the cessation of doubt and regards intransigence as a sign of religious devotion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This perennial conflict between faith and reason, the tendency to unquestioningly submit to a higher power and to seek truth in accordance with one&amp;rsquo;s own merits has for long plagued the minds of sagacious men and brings us back to the aforementioned question. What is the nature of faith? Far from being absolute certainty in a set of propositions, what lies at the heart of faith, as paradoxical as it may seem, is doubt. Historically the story of the fall of Lucifer had been increasingly interpreted as an alarming reminder of the ramifications that would ensue if one disobeyed God&amp;rsquo;s commands. But a deeper more profound reading of the narrative indicates that the devil&amp;rsquo;s greatest sin was not that he dared to question a specific God but that he questioned the very notion that there exists things which might exceed the bounds of his all too finite comprehension. As a consequence, his rebellious nature was not born out of doubt towards God but out of a lack of skepticism towards himself. This sophisticated interplay between faith and doubt appeared to me as the cardinal aspect of the entire narrative and that the fundamental challenge of all religious endeavours was to balance these two proclivities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In an era of extremes where moderate political and religious opinions are considered to be a sign of weakness and reservation, the story of the primordial fall acquires new meaning as a cautionary tale of certainty for it teaches us that faith could never be truly cultivated in the absence of doubt because faith does not reaffirm what we do not know but emphasizes that which we couldn&amp;rsquo;t.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On The Nature of Dreams</title>
      <link>https://noumenalnotions.space/essays/on_the_nature_of_dreams/</link>
      <guid>https://noumenalnotions.space/essays/on_the_nature_of_dreams/</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Apr 2022 22:14:00 IST</pubDate>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The nature of dreams has always eluded psychologists ever since the human psyche and all its manifestations were subject to the scrutiny of scientific thinking. In the past, the application of empirical methods in the appraisal of mental phenomena seemed obsolete given the prevalent notion that there was nothing novel to be discovered in the frontier of the human mind since the contents of the former were supposedly identical with the materials of consciousness. The existence of a terra incognita within the domain of psychological processes was neither speculated nor ascribed much credence for men were too fond of the idea that they were masters of their own houses. But in light of the discovery of the unconscious as an elementary factor of the human psyche and its supreme significance in the determination of the true meaning of psychic phenomena, this ill conceived notion that all mental processes were encapsulated by the horizon of consciousness was soon to be shown as utterly insufficient in accounting for the facts unearthed in the investigation of neurotic disorders and as a consequence evinced the presence of influences which escaped the narrow scope of conscious ideation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nonetheless the concept of the unconscious is still greeted with ridicule and mockery in circles that are inclined to reduce all forms of psychological suffering to physiological processes whose subtle nature is held responsible for obscuring our assumption of an organic cause to these afflictions. It went against all medical convention to even entertain an assumption to the contrary since what else could possibly give rise to such strange illnesses? Surely all of these forms of mental afflictions one way or another must emanate from a deformity of the brain or some other biological predicate whose seemingly absent nature doesnt necessarily entail its non existence. To attribute the cause of such maladies to something as nebulous as the human psyche and its strange inner mechanisms strikes us as odd for it appears to depart from the sober tradition of empiricism with which the scientific community and all of its factions are intimately acquainted with. Nonetheless the consistent failure to demonstrate that all forms of psychological afflictions can exclusively be reduced to a somatic origin leads one to suggest that either our understanding of brain physiology is woefully limited or perhaps the content of our own minds are not as transparent as we assume them to be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This decision to ascribe an equal significance to mental processes as relatively independent from its physiological underpinnings, in my opinion, marked a decisive moment in the history of empirical thought. Although it seems pseudoscientific to outline the nature of processes whose essence can only be inferred indirectly, the hypothesis generated from such inferences are still bound by the same pragmatic demarcations as any other. In such instances, the scientific method evolves into a form of instrumentalism where the utility of an idea in the domain of its appropriate application is found to be the only viable measure of its truth. Not only does this lend credibility to attempts of analyzing psychological processes but also dispenses with accusations of any unbounded capriciousness on the part of the investigators who undertake such an enterprise. But what precisely gives rise to the overwhelming reluctance we often encounter against the existence of unconscious trains of thought which is stipulated to influence our mode of conduct. Is it merely a reaction against the overtly unscientific demeanour of such an idea or does it perhaps ironically indicate the manifestation of a prejudice which owes its potency for being of the very nature it seeks to dismiss?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Partly the reason why the entire concept of the unconscious as being an indispensable part of our mental apparatus is met with much resistance is because it seems to undermine the amount of control we often assume to exercise over our choices. In the past and perhaps even now, the decisions we make which finds it consequent expression in our actions is generally held to be the inexorable product of ones volition. As a result, any mode of conduct which infringed upon the status quo was perceived as a direct consequence of thoughtful deliberation or in the least was regarded to be influenced by some amount of premeditation. Naturally, any framework which ,wittingly or unwittingly, cast these ideals under a questionable light was dismissed from the very outset under the pretext of ascribing its origins to fringe intellectuals whose postulations must have been nothing but a desperate coup to secure attention and respectability. To surmise that these unconscious influences profoundly shaped the way we act and perceived each other threatened some of the fundamental assumptions of our social institutions that relied on concepts of accountability and justice for its proper functioning. All of these misgivings appears to have reinforced the prejudice against the utility of any subjective phenomena, such as dreams which happens to be object of our inquiry, and has for long obstructed our forays in discovering the true nature of the human mind. If however, we cast aside any such ill informed preconceptions for the sake of a dispassionate inquiry the importance of the unconscious and the unique relationship it shares with the phenomena of dreams soon begins to crystallize.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The idea of supposing the existence of independent mental agencies within the confines of the human mind is quite strange in its insistence that the individual is not an integrated whole but an amalgamation of warring sub personalities each pursuing their own ends. And the fact that most of these agencies remain unconscious and influence our mode of conduct, although widely recognized these days, still paradoxically fails to revise our views on the inordinate confidence we possess on having an accurate knowledge of ourselves. A confidence which has both contributed to the ignorance of others experience and our own. But if we accept the existence of a mental landscape, termed the unconscious, unmarked by the treads of human thought , what kind of implications does such a notion entail and how can we possibly hope to shed light on something which by its very definition is unconscious? Although the contents of this dark frontier for the most part lies beyond human perception, one could still infer the nature of its processes and the general characteristics which permeate them through the investigation of phenomena that has become conscious but whose origin evidently lies in its obscure counterpart. And the most accessible means we have at our disposal of such a nature happens to be the perplexing occurrence of dreams.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The aforementioned discussion of the unconscious and the tenability of psychological investigations might seem irrelevant in our attempt to understand dreams but in my opinion, it puts things in their proper context so that one can fully realize the foundations from which this seemingly inexplicable phenomena becomes a bit more intelligible. At first glance, a dream strikes us as nothing more than a series of nonsensical fragments whose utterly incoherent nature prompts us to speculate that it must be a product of mere happenstance. Consequently, any meaning which it might seem to impart on the observer must also be of an accidental nature, requiring an incalculable amount of effort to piece together its arcane subtexts. This sharp contrast between the logical coherence of normal ideational processes and the incomprehensibility of dreams construed in that light is what primarily contributes to our repudiation of them as unnecessary by products of some physiological process. But underneath this casual dismissal lies the tacit assumption that any meaningful product of human thought must also necessarily bear the crest of reason and intelligbility. It is quite inconceivable that how an idea which is divested of these qualities can produce something that one could deem even remotely meaningful and owing to our rational turn of the mind, even remotely comprehensible. If we are to grant these obscure representations the benefit of the doubt and assume that it conceals some coherent train of thought, where would we begin?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A renowned psychologist named Sigmund Freud directed most his attention to the very same questions that we are now beginning to unravel. Prior to his publication of The Interpretation of Dreams, no serious consideration had been given to these nocturnal instantiations or to its peculiar relationship with psycho-pathological disorders. Freud however, saw in them something that no one had ever seen before. An expression of a mode of thinking which betrayed its archaic character and as a consequence presented an avenue through which the fundamental determinants of psychic life could be properly investigated. Early on, Freud was convinced that due to its archaic nature, dreams could not be understood in the sense that any normal idea could and required a method of explication which accounted for the esoteric language that it spoke. Gathering knowledge from his various empirical researches, he eventually concluded that a dream in spite of its ostensibly ridiculous facade was underpinned by a series of unconscious ideas that underwent a dramatic change in the course of it being rendered conscious. Freud, for the most part, attributed the dreams lack of coherence to psychic mechanisms which were responsible for converting these ideas to its pictorial representation and also to distort them in order to pass a moral censor which actively resisted the illumination of dreams in its unadulterated form. Through the application of a method which he termed psychoanalysis, Freud was able to imbue meaning and coherence into a phenomena that for most people was too recondite to be taken seriously. But the more salient aspect of this discovery however still remained far from obvious.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nietzsche in Beyond Good and Evil wrote that What we experience in a dream, provided we experience it frequently, finally is as much a part of the collective household of our souls as anything truly experienced. At first, reading these lines instilled a queer sense of skepticism for how was I to believe that a dream, clearly distinguished by its unreality and ephemeral nature, could exert as much influence in me as events which transpired in waking life. It struck me as absurd to hold in equal footing subjective events such as dreams which most individuals regard to be fleeting moments in their nocturnal life with objective events that had a seemingly real impact in the course of our lives. I presumed that the acceptance of such an idea ran the risk of loosing a firm foundation which markedly separated the sane individual from the mentally depraved. However the implications of a Freudian understanding of dreams coupled with Nietzsches aphorism suggests that such a notion may perhaps reveal some fundamental truths about the riddle of human experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both Nietzsche and Freud in their attempts to understand dreams has managed to articulate certain fundamental truths about the nature of the human mind which the zeitgeist of our time has left unheeded. The primary reason why Freuds ideas on human psychology which centered around the unconscious aroused such distaste in his time is because it sought to paint a picture of inner experience that mirrored the objective world. For most of human history, men have always taken it for granted that the knowledge they possessed of themselves was self evident because of the assumption that our thoughts and feelings were entirely transparent to the subject that conceived it. Although a few sagacious men had come to recognize the imprudence of such a presumption, they had no means at their disposal to demonstrate why it was incorrect. Freud, who endeavoured to explain the discrepancies of mental life through the postulation of the unconscious, not only showed the world that both the scope and the depth of inner experience was equally as vast as objective reality and but also that dreams where the primary means through which one could comprehend this reality. What is even more astounding is the fact that the insights one could glean from these phantasms, although belonging to a world markedly different from that of waking life could still reveal fundamental truths about human experience that can be of invaluable importance even outside the fantastical landscape from which it originated. It seemed to me that this intimate relationship between the macrocosmic order of the universe and microcosm of the human psyche is what Nietzsche had alluded to. And dreams placed within this context appear to us as heralds of a world within us that the critical mind has begun to seldom understand.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Requiem for The Past</title>
      <link>https://noumenalnotions.space/essays/a_requiem_for_the_past/</link>
      <guid>https://noumenalnotions.space/essays/a_requiem_for_the_past/</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Jul 2021 22:13:59 IST</pubDate>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Among all the prolific intellectuals who had come to exercise a decisive influence on my opinions, it was Carl Jung, most of all, whom I had profoundly admired for his remarkable felicity and astounding erudition. At the very outset of acquainting myself with his brilliant corpus, the fact that he spoke of archaic literature as though they were of the utmost relevance to the present era seemed exceedingly strange for a young liberal like myself. I have always held the opinion that the past was merely a store house of the failures of our forefathers and that there was no utility whatsoever in sifting through those seemingly nonsensical texts to find hidden wisdom that could supposedly deliver us from human follies. I did acknowledge the fact that our ancestors had made some contributions to the success of our civilizations but how could they possibly assert anything of relevance ten or twenty years from their inevitable demise?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To my modern sensibilities it seemed extremely far fetched and perhaps even absolutely ludicrous to suggest the idea that the contemporary questions humanity struggles with could be answered if instead of looking far ahead into the future one looked far back into the past. That theologians and philosophers who lived in immemorial times that were primarily characterized by ignorance and primitive superstitions magically stumbled upon perennial wisdom which if lost would ensure our own peril. Jung however firmly believed that the ghost of our ancestors had a lot more to teach even after their morbid dissolution and dedicated most of his life in the pursuit of archaic knowledge so that he can listen to their faint wailings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This principle difference in attitude that Jung had fortunately harboured sparked much controversy among his contemporaries for it appeared to be diametrically opposed to the scientific reductionism that was perpetuated by major schools of thought in his time. In an era of enlightenment where revolutionary thinkers like Freud and Adler had made unparalleled contributions to the realm of empirical psychology by their zeal for rigorous methodology, it seems quite obvious why Jungs ostensibly mystical preoccupations were either met with abject reluctance or well-nigh hostility.  It is much more expedient for the rational intellect to simply disregard  archaic conceptions as feeble products of an infant psyche because the alternative seemed to suggest that the world was far more mysterious than what its reasonable denizens made it out to be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The reason Jung had sought to integrate the age old conceptions of his ancestors prevalently stigmatized with his own intellectual orientation was because he was much more likely to attribute the incoherence of ancient ideas to his own cognitive ineptitude than that of his forefathers. Although this intellectual humility might seem relatively unimportant compared to the feats of his materialistic counterparts, it was precisely this fundamental difference in opinion that made him one of the most eminent psychologists to have ever existed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the chief insights that beset Jung while he scoured through the immense literature of antiquity was that any standpoint which intended to view archaic notions in the light of a scientific context betrayed the existence of a grave categorical error.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He believed that most of the criticisms and polemics directed against religion and the entire corpus of the past emerged from this fundamentally absurd insistence evaluating the tenability of these ideas from an exclusively scientific context. Ever since the inception of post-experimentalist thought, people have for some reason taken for granted that the fundamental tenets of empiricism has always been self evident, even in the times of our forefathers. This incorrect presumption fueled the proclivity to translate modern psychology back into the times of antiquity, while heedlessly ignoring the primitive context. But Jung, however, saw through the mists that shrouded the essence of these texts and as a consequence penetrated into the deepest strata of human consciousness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dispensing with the assumption that these age old formulations reflected empirical truths, Jung sought to discover what precisely constituted the meaning of these ideas that have survived the arduous test of time. The destiny of entire civilizations which ruled over millions of individuals for thousands of years were predicated upon the very principles that we now choose to casually denigrate under the pretext of furthering rational thought. If the ideals in question were simply ideological drivel deliberately contrived by the oligarchy to control the masses, or perhaps the product of a morbid human imagination conjured up to appease the demands of our existential dilemmas, how could they possibly exert such a numinous influence on the exponents of such beliefs? Is the lofty world of gods merely a phantasm of the archaic mind concocted for a necessity that we have long outgrown, or does it somehow represent truths whose obscure nature partly owes its explanation to the predominantly materialistic outlook of our time?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In spite of being absolutely certain that theological formulations could not be eschewed simply because of its incompatibility with enlightened rationalism, Jung soon realised that effecting a proper synthesis of the two was perhaps one of the most daring ventures anyone could undertake, for it required him to garner knowledge from extremely diverse and arcane subjects that were blithely ignored due to its mystical veneer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However it seems to me that the decisive contribution Jung had made to the dialectic of religion was discovering its psychological dimensions, whose existence prompted him to reflect on what constituted the fundamental elements of the human psyche. Unlike his Freudian contemporaries who endeavoured to reduce the complexity of our psychological dispositions to the instinct of sexuality, Jung believed that such a frame of reference was grotesquely skewed because it could never account for the multitude of expressions that we find in bygone literature.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Regarding theological conceptions as merely a sublimation of primordial sexual desires drastically oversimplified the richness that they evidently possessed and manifested itself to any dispassionate inquirer of truth, among whom Jung enjoyed a prominent position. Nonetheless, he wasnt interested in a philosophical reconciliation as much as the experiential underpinnings which occasioned the numinousity that was often associated with such ideas. From a phenomenological perspective, it seemed irrelevant to ask whether God was an objective tangible being who actually existed, because the experience of God, and the plethora of concomitant theological frameworks, is by no means contingent upon the former. More than anything else he realised that this phenomenology of God was the most pervasive human experience documented across all levels of culture in all epochs and testified to the immensely deep roots that connected us to the mystifying past of ancestral humanity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Discovering psychological undercurrents that influenced the religious train of thought enabled Jung to develop a conceptual framework through which he could explain profuse manifestations in the divine landscape. Intellectually speaking, though his ideas deserve wide commendation from all those who have laboured tirelessly to illuminate the knowledge of our ancestors, I think what is even more significant is to recognise the attitude Jung had espoused throughout the course of his life for therein lies the true pearls of his wisdom.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From a modern perspective, considering the entire body of religious literature soon imparts a feeling of utter repugnance on anyone who was brought up in the auspices of enlightened ideals. The unprecedented material progress the rational mind has effected through the purveyors of science has altogether threatened the viability of religious dogma which appeared to be diametrically opposed to the lucid thinking characteristic of that era. By completely disregarding means of knowledge that transcended the sensory apparatus, the rationalist worldview sought to liberate human kind from the delusions they had formerly entertained. This process of rendering all other proclivities in man subservient to the unswerving judgment of the intellect defined the enlightenment and produced all the unforseen material prosperity we recognise around us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although outwardly it appeared as though we were becoming increasingly wealthier by forgoing the propensity of our forebears, the vestiges of the past aroused inner exigencies which could be seldom soothed by a mere proliferation of inanimate opulence. On the contrary, the solution to this inner predicament required a radical change in our understanding of what constituted human nature and most importantly necessitated a recognition of the inexplicable bond we shared with the past.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In spite of being the product of a time that extolled the virtues of rationalism, Jung still endeavored to illustrate why the religious corpus had remained relevant to the enlightened modern consciousness. Although innumerable attempts have been made to effect a reconciliation of these two divergent worldviews, it seems to me that what separates Jung from the rest of the cohort was his peculiar instinct for the wisdom of the past. As far as Jung was concerned, the past was fraught with secrets and arcane knowledge waiting to be unearthed by individuals who were free of prejudice and displayed an immeasurable resolve to discover the truth regardless of where it may lead them. This passion for truth is what caused Jung to venture into forgotten lands in the hopes of finding knowledge that could potentially transform our understanding of archaic frameworks. Notwithstanding the complete reconceptualization this would have on my conceptions of the past, what appeared to be even more salient is the effects it would have on what truth precisely consisted of. Something that Jung himself had left implicit in his writings so that even his most astute readers would struggle to comprehend its subtle implications.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The reason I suppose Jung holds such special place in the pantheon of intellectuals I have encountered is because he makes one realise the significance of all that is left unsaid. Expanding his horizons beyond the materialistic confines of rationality, he pushes further to discover the very nucleus of religiosity by diligently perusing ancient manuscripts only to discover that there is a world of meaning buried underneath. In addition to making such a remarkable discovery, it seems to me that Jung also provides an avenue through which we can better understand the immutable connection we share with the past.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The modern world with all its scientific progress looks down upon history as a time where mental infirmities abound. Thus any idea which appear to be the product of such a time must be inconsequential compared to the lofty conceptions born out of a rational mindset. Nonetheless, by discerning the fact that myth and religion does not reflect objective truth, we move one step closer in resolving this age old predicament but more importantly realise that human nature is the source of an endless mystery that is far from being rendered comprehensible. As trivial as it may sound, this reflection constitutes the very essence of Jungian thought and forms the necessary precondition through which the past transforms itself from a fleeting spectre of forgotten times into an ever evolving edifice manifesting itself through the individual.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And it was precisely this verity that motivated Jung to seek answers in the dark embrasures of religious thinking for unlike most of his contemporaries he believed that truth was often complex and inconceivably nuanced that it can only be grasped in the farthest realms of intuition&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Allure to Darkness</title>
      <link>https://noumenalnotions.space/essays/the_allure_to_darkness/</link>
      <guid>https://noumenalnotions.space/essays/the_allure_to_darkness/</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 31 Mar 2021 22:14:00 IST</pubDate>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;That is not dead which can eternal lie and with strange aeons even death may die&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have never considered myself as a person with morbid inclinations until I chanced upon these lines while reading H.P Lovecraft&amp;rsquo;s most renowned Gothic novella, The Call of Cthullu. One of the first things that made an impression upon me about Lovecraft was the irony in his name since love is supposed to be the polar opposite of anything that could be deemed as grotesque or unnatural. Nonetheless, this misgiving rapidly gave way once I realised his literal ingenuity. Within a few minutes into the book, I found his literary prose to be oddly captivating for some reason. It was as though using his words, he was capable of arousing the most terrifying images humanly conceivable in the readers&amp;rsquo; mind with exceptional clarity but in the process fettered one with chains of curiosity that rendered any chances of putting down the book, highlyimplausible. At first, it proved to be quite difficult and tiresome to understand his convoluted sentences refined for aesthetic appeal but with a little amount of perseverance I became extremely fond of his prosaic style and managed to breeze through his sentences with almost no effort.Finishingthebookwithinafewhours, I seemed to have been overwhelmed by a queer sense of nostalgia while wondering how the utterly terrifying things that I just read could exercise such a magical influence on someone whos always despised any work of horror most of his life. Among the innumerable Gothic fiction produced for entertainment, it seemed to me that the Lovecraftian universe did not possess any distinctive characteristics that would set it apart from the rest of its counterparts but soon after, I became quite convinced that this analysis was painfully superficial and that the object of its criticism warranted a much more diligent scrutiny.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thereby began my relentless pursuit to understand this strange liking that I took towards H.P Lovecraft&amp;rsquo;s nocturnal monstrosities. I started perusing the internet for every Lovecraftian work of horrorhithertopublished, from At The Mountain of Madness to Shadow Over Insmouth, incessantly devouring what I considered to be some of the greatest works of fiction ever written. With each book that I managed to read within hours of its discovery, my appreciation for Lovecraft and the entire realm of morbid aspirations grew correspondingly unobscure but so did my perplexion with this peculiar fondness that I discovered within myself. For as long as I can remember, I have always shown a marked aversion to things that are generally permeated by a hideous undertone because of my encounters with uncommonlyfrightfulcircumstances. Some of the earliest memories that I retained from my childhood were of an exceedingly morbid nature which I suppose greatly contributed to my abhorrence of anything dark and twisted. And the tribulations of life that besets one and shatters any appearance of normality should have reinforced my prejudice against anything ghastly but here I was, utterly fascinated by these seemingly grotesque figures of darkness. The paradoxical nature of this novel fascination captivated even further and I soon became obsessed with fully expounding this new found appreciation. I started to feel that the Cthullu Mythos - Lovecraft&amp;rsquo;s fictional universe - directly spoke to a part of myself that I didn&amp;rsquo;t even know existed and consequently prompted a deep reflection into the dark recesses of my human soul.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was during this period of introspective contemplation that I fully realised that the peculiarities did not lie in Lovecraft&amp;rsquo;s novellas but rather in the subject in which it excited much attention. This realisation came us a complete surprise to someone like me whos always been portrayed as a seemingly innocuous person; and this attempt to impart an identity upon me was not met with much resistance since I firmly believed that the quality of being innocuous was inherently a virtue. Thus I revelled in my supposedly unwavering moral rectitude, harbouring the unshakeable conviction that I most certainly contributed to solving the overarching moral nihilism that characterizes our current society. Nonetheless, protecting this illusion that I was an avatar of moral purity proved to be beyond the bounds of my capabilities once I confronted the darkness that lied within me. Clearly, my Lovecraftian run of the readings unwittingly lead to a discovery that immediately won my disapproval for it implied the line that separated me and the people that I have despised most of my life was much more ill defined than I would like to admit. A conviction from which I derived most of my moral fortitude for so long foundered upon this startling discovery and ultimately lead to what could only be described as a metamorphosis, for this was the time that I became intimately acquainted with Carl Jung&amp;rsquo;s idea of the shadow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From a Jungian perspective, the shadow is simply defined as an individual&amp;rsquo;s inferior qualities that has been repressed as a consequence of a moral conflict with conscious norms or ideals. It is the part of the personality that has been ignored as being too hideous or immoral and thus sinks to the unconscious, exerting its influence on our conscious mode of conduct behind the veil. Encountering these descriptions while reading Jung struck me as quite strange and I struggled to discern whether if it was my lack of ingenuity and wisdom that caused such bafflement or my inexperience with psychological literature. Although most of what Jung said seemed to lie in domains that I have hitherto never dared to even acknowledge, I deeply resonated with his writings and acquired an inexplicable impression that suggested its supreme importance to my psychological well being. So I sought to dispense with this feeling of apparent remoteness and resolved to understand his ideas in spite of its sheer complexity. Within a few months, I managed to obtain a reasonable understanding of the Jungian framework and felt competent enough to engage in various discourse pertaining to psychology and comparativemythology hoping to glean insights that would  aidmycomprehension ofhisarcanesubtexts. But this abstract acquisition however was not immediately followed by any form of spiritual change like I had hoped. In spite of my new found ability to adequately reformulate Jung&amp;rsquo;s conceptions on my own terms, I felt that I would never truly understand the essence of his writings unless I weaved his ideals through my own personal narrative. I was once again reminded of the difference between verbal representations and the underlying substance they sought to circumscribe and ventured to establish a connection between these concepts and my own subjectivity. This endeavour nonetheless proved to be much more difficult than I had presumed since the requisite material that would allow me to establish such a bond was wholly rendered unconscious by my infantile attitude. On the brink of desertion, this undertaking was surprisingly resuscitated by my encounter with the morbid anthology of Lovecraftian fiction and unearthed parts of myself that were simply too painful to confront. Parts that would constitute the impalpable connection I later formed with the Jungian Opus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My encounter with the Gothic writings of H.P Lovecraft and the subsequent reflections prompted by the former brought forth a wave of dreams fraught with unspeakable horror and dread. The dreams, unlike what one would expect, did not possess any typical qualities of Gothic fiction that I had lately perused but seemed to reveal contents that were extremely personal in nature. During its initial stages, I was exceedingly overwhelmed by these strange ordeals and struggled to grapple with them due to the unprecedented nature of their problem but their repeated occurrence however alleviated the fear that was normally associated such experiences and paved a way that would greatly further my understanding of psychological afflictions and human nature in general. So instead of running away from the spectres of darkness that plagued me at night, I resolved to confront them and elucidate their archaic forms of representations in spite of its sheer ambiguity. Unlike most other psychologists of his time who considered dreams as nothing more than a trivial abnormality that did not warrant much attention, Jung regarded them as direct manifestations of unconscious activity whose message was of the utmost significance to the dreamer and solely attributed its apparent incoherence as a consequence of personal ineptitude. I instantly sympathized with Jungs conceptions on the importance of dream activity and started to realise that ignoring my nightmares would not contribute to their much desired imminent disappearance. Thus I directed my undivided attention to the nocturnal part of my existence and willingly confronted the products of my unconscious morbidities. Notwithstanding the fact that I was utterly terrified by their abject grotesqueness, I began to notice furtive allusions I seemed to associate with distant memories that have since long been buried. Subsequently, a flood of associations rushed in like a storm, mostly serving to instantiate the immorality of my past actions and motivations and which inevitably lead me to question the moral nature of my existence. I was completely engrossed by this problem, so to speak, and constantly searched for justifications that would fortify my cherished illusion but those attempts forever remained in vain. I was invariably obligated to find a way to assimilate these new found contents that were unearthed in the process of this demoralising introspection but could only do so by answering a question that seemed thoroughly inscrutable. A question that forced me to reconsider the very nature of darkness itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A problem that I merely regarded to be nothing more than a trivial idiosyncrasy that would simply contribute to my long list of queer peculiarities proved to be a much larger predicament whose relevance encapsulated every individual that comprised current societies and as a consequence demanded their most fervent attention. Nonetheless, the people that I often encountered seemed to remain completely impervious to such moral conflicts whilst I appeared to be foredoomed to live a life eternally characterized by profound psychological disunion. I simply could not rest content with the fact that I harboured qualities of such moral decadence and took elaborate pains to discover the reasons for why I possessed those traits. Although comparatively speaking, I could be described as a moral person who did not pose any danger to himself or to those around him, the point of my concern was not so much the things I had done in the past which qualified as immoral but the potentialities that were illuminated in the process of this laboriousselfreflection. I was soon confronted with the question on how exactly would one reconcile goodness with the capacity to inflictunduesufferingonothers. Isn&amp;rsquo;t it rational to presume that the absence of malevolence is what truly constitutes as being good? Or does evil paradoxically form the necessary precondition for genuine morality that individuals strive towards? But the question that I found to be the most disconcerting was why did such supposedly trivial issues that no one ever bothered about and which evidently possessed a morbid demeanourbe utterlycaptivating? The task of answering these questions occupied the forefront of my consciousness but any solution that I stumbled upon seemed to lie far beyond the bounds of my comprehension. I was no distinguished moral philosopher who could divine generalized conclusions about the moral nature of our existence but simply a precocious adolescent whose taste for morbid things aroused in him an inexplicable disquietude. In spite of my apparent cluelessness, my intuition lead me to believe that the series of aforementioned questions could all be resolved to that problem which troubled me the most. What precisely constituted the allure to darkness?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And there I was once again, struggling to understand the inexplicable source of my morbid fascinations and perhaps even of the existence of darkness itself. The first image that one recalls in the face of darkness and evil is obviously the Devil, a widely disseminated religious figure whose existence could very well account for all the malevolence that abounds in the world. But as I looked upon history and the catastrophes wrought by tyrants and oligarchs characterized by an insatiable thirst for power, the proposition that the devil was the only cause of evil seemed unconvincing since it clearly was the deliberate act of individuals that lead to such catastrophes. The devil could very well have tempted those individuals to commit such atrocities instead of doing the deed himself but nonetheless, the outcome was still contingent upon their willful subordination to the potent forces of darkness. Therefore naturally, one might assume that bringing about goodness in this world is merely a matter of resisting the alluring exhortations of Satan and fortifying oneself against him by strongly adhering to their respective religious doctrines. But the belief in the objective validity of religious precepts however has been greatly undermined since the inception of post experimentalist thought and the devil in the modern era seems like nothing more than a fleeting fantasy that warrants our utmost contempt and ridicule. Even from an orthodox religious perspective, admitting to the existence of the Devil is seldom followed by a diligent survey that attempts to expound what precisely makes him evil. We either ascribe no significance whatsoever to this well known figure or exalt him to such heights of decadence that even showing the slightest of interest on the context within which he is placed is perceived as sinful or well nigh daemonic. As I appropriated a refined corpus of knowledge pertaining to the phenomenon of malevolence and resentment it seemed highly likely that the follies of human civilization is not solely a consequence of forsaking the idea of God. It is also partly because we have underestimated and profoundly misunderstood what the Devil actually stands for. And most importantly failed to recognise what it is that draws people towards darkness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The conclusions that I derived from what appeared to be an insipid rumination about Lovecraftian horror proved to be revolutionary for I have never been the same person since then. One of the first things I realized in my arduous contemplations that would help me answer the aforementioned questions was the fact that the nature of our moral judgements largely depend on the context within which they are manifested. So unlike what most people would suppose evil could never be sufficiently elucidated to a series of abstract descriptions for every aspect of human experience necessarily harbours a paradoxical quality. Anything that could be deemed as a mark of goodness and benevolence might very well seem undoubtedly evil if the presumptions that underlie such a frame of reference is slightly altered. This is perhaps why evil is best construed as a personality because only a living entity could best approximate the true nature of a dynamic process and any abstraction that one might employ to understand such an idea is invariably distorted. Despite the apparent simplicity of this observation, the implications that it entailed had far reaching effects on my overarching worldview because it seemed to presage a glimmer of hope that would finally alleviate my dismal state of affairs. Contrary to their allegorical usage, I eventually recognised that darkness and evil were not identical in nature because the formers enclave confined a much larger aspect of human experience than the latter. And because of our proclivity to tenaciously protect the edifices from which we derive much of our certainty both of those words remained insufficiently discriminated and as a consequence anything that even dared to transgress already established ideals was unthinkingly conceptualized as a harbinger of evil. The reason I suppose darkness exercises such an influence on curious individuals like myself is because it also represents latent potential. It represents everything that has hitherto remained outside the bounds of our chartered territory and beckons people who present the courage and ingenuity to rise up to the occasion that would profoundly expand the domain of human understanding. This morbid curiosity might very well threaten everything that we have ever worked for and might even prove to be extremely dangerous for the individual who undertakes such a courageous enterprise but any alternative that seems superficially desirable leads to a much larger catastrophe than one might expect. It is indispensable to take into account the ever prevailing darkness that surrounds human experience because any failure to do so would be what truly constitutes the evil mode of being.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Enabling me to discern the evil I encountered without, the insights I had gleaned also allowed me to reconcile the immorality that I found within. Comprehending the fact that evil was merely pride and the voluntary refusal to admit ones fallibility, I realized that my former actions that bore the mark of malice was in fact the source of my greatest strength for without its existence my understanding of evil would have forever retained its premature naivety. Soon after this reconceptualization, the nightmares that had often plagued me at night grew increasingly infrequent and eventually withered away. The dissolution of my former personality and the consequent plunge into the depths of chaos was followed by a profound enlargement of my conscious understanding of the world and of myself. It was as though I was involuntarily disillusioned by transpersonal forces who had laid life bare in all its glorious failures and apprehensions and as a result instilled a deep seated humility that would perhaps never fail to remind me of my personal inadequacies. Although this triumphant victory over the forces of darkness so to speak was preceded by a period of intense misery and despair, the subsequent wisdom that was unearthed during this process proved to be invaluable in my pursuit of self knowledge. I was finally able to fully comprehend Jungs notion about the shadow and how ones conscious orientation towards it would aid in the formation of an integrated personality. But this hard earned acquisition however did not in the least undermine the vitality of my profuse inner life. On the contrary, my dreams had only proliferated in number and firmly established the importance of my psychological reality that I could no longer ignore for I had beheld the light nested within the darkness that beckoned me.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Forgotten Art of Reading</title>
      <link>https://noumenalnotions.space/essays/the_forgotten_art_of_reading/</link>
      <guid>https://noumenalnotions.space/essays/the_forgotten_art_of_reading/</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Mar 2021 22:14:00 IST</pubDate>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;During the early stages of my formative years, I have always wondered how people derived such immense pleasure from reading books. To my puerile intellect it seemed that they were nothing more than recycled wood that bore bleak sentences strung together for pretentious individuals who simply wanted to project themselves as intellectuals. No one in my vicinity had sought to reconstitute this primitive definition of mine and I naively assumed that the entirety of knowledge was fully encapsulated by the academic subjects I was taught. That the preoccupation of reading a book was just another prerogative of the aristocracy I had to confront with profound indifference.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Therefore the constricted horizons I possessed came to pre-eminently characterize the seemingly diverse perspectives I presumed to uphold. Although my contemporary perceptions indicated that my opinions were relatively novel, in retrospect I can hardly discern any distinctive element from what seems now to be incoherent fragments of a thoughtless meandering. Since my intellectual life had been wholly confined to the strictly academic environment my school had to offer, I seldom felt the need to pursue any curiosities I might have harboured outside the regular scholastic enterprise. Like most of my peers I had been completely persuaded that an educational institution is the only place that could efficiently facilitate true learning and any other mode of acquisition was bound to end in miserable failure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In spite of being intensely passionate about ideas all my life, I only understood the ineffable significance of reading a book years later when one of my acquaintances unwittingly instilled a deep seated appreciation for arcane literature. It was only then I realised theres much more to this ostensibly insipid process of assimilating information than what meets the eye.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is no overstatement to say that I was opened to an enormous world of awe and sheer wonder when I first acquired the wisdom necessary to penetrate into the true essence of an object that I had heretofore regarded with remarkable callousness. What I had so far conceived as a prosaic human artifice concocted for the entertainment of a pronounced minority seemed to conceal a nature far more interesting than I had ever presumed before. Strangely however, my initial amazement was not so much directed at the peculiar qualities I perceived to be emanating from a book as how I had managed to stay oblivious towards something for so long that now seemed positively magical.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was naturally inclined to attribute my cause of ignorance to the kind of deprived environment my school had assiduously strived to foster but soon realized it would be dishonest if I were to do that exclusively. But regardless of what might have contributed to the stark indifference that was now utterly shattered by this newfound experience, a book that once fared as a pale object compared to other modes of acquisition seemed to transcend all prior representation I ascribed to it. Although its constituent elements were made of nothing but ink and paper mostly bound together by a thicker version of the latter, its experiential significance far outweighed any assumptions one would make solely from its objective properties. And a closer examination of what might constitute this significance yielded a richer store of knowledge than I had ever hoped to glean from what I had long reckoned as a mere manifestation of utter bleakness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I eventually realised that a book unlike what I had supposed before could be best conceptualized as a gateway into the minds of various authors as opposed to a static representation intended to communicate stale ideas. It is much more akin to an ingenious instrument people have devised to circumscribe parts of themselves into an objective entity that anyone could access as long as he possessed the literary prowess to comprehend it. And this entity is often a product of profound deliberations on the subject it wishes to expound and usually bears an unmistakable relationship with books of a similar nature. This relationship that appeared to weave together the entire corpus of knowledge was perhaps the most striking quality that I recognised to be a part of a book.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No matter how idiosyncratic an authors opinion seemed to be I noticed that it almost unerringly contained remnants of some other author who shared similar aspirations. Among the more esoteric kind, the writers were capable of making connections across extremely diverse domains of knowledge that it was uncanny how they were capable of divining such brilliant ideas whilst giving the impression of expending no intellectual effort whatsoever. But amidst these feelings of admiration and incredulity, I also seemed to recognise a qualitative shift in my mode of learning that I had never anticipated. With every book that I read in order to extricate myself from the intellectual ignorance that constantly plagued me, I slowly began to realise that a sufficient understanding of an authors publication necessitated a subtle comprehension of the entire corpus from which he derived much of his ideas. Thus it seemed to me that I was conceptually obligated to acquaint myself with a much larger framework of knowledge than what the book had actually curtailed if I was to understand the seemingly isolated work in all its entirety.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The former discovery, notwithstanding its antithetical nature to the ideals on specialized learning I had entertained so far, seemed to elicit a deeper reflection into the very structure of knowledge which I had paid scant attention to in the course of my academic endeavours. Thereby what had merely started as a resuscitation of some latent propensity that had long remained buried furnished an uncommon rumination about the framework of ideas themselves that one seldom heeds to in the course of his formal education.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unlike what I had normally expected to obtain from conscientiously reading books, the ideas that I assimilated unexpectedly rendered me cognizant to a complex dynamic of relationships that connected all the different realms of the intellectual enterprise. And this interconnectedness that I perceived, furthermore, seemed to profoundly influence the choice of my next read which consequently produced an organic growth of the knowledge I amassed every single time I completed a literary work. As a consequence of this strange developmental process, the initial aspirations I had harboured for the hard sciences slowly enlarged upon a wider frontier that also encapsulated a significant part of the humanities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Starting from a subject that one usually considers to be completely divorced  from the social sciences, I inadvertently found myself in the abysmal depths of philosophy and psychology through a relentless pursuit of the aforementioned theoretical link. The strict demarcation of academic disciplines that I had grown accustomed to seemed to be an ineffective method of education in light of these observations for the mechanical incorporation of a set of facts is far inferior to an acquisitional process that predominantly relied on the pursuit of unmitigated curiosity.It seemed to me that this mode of learning could easily dispense with the boredom that one usually encounters in the canonical method inasmuch as he finds an axis through which he can connect various disciplines with his own domain of curiosity. An axis that I myself had come to discover simply by reading.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These reflections however did not in the least prompt me to completely deplore the concept of specialized learning but rather seemed to suggest that confining ones orientation to a constricted domain of knowledge can profoundly hamper the development of ones character in all its entirety. Ever since Adam Smith first proposed his ideas on the division of labour, the concept of specialization has increasingly disseminated itself over all the facets of human life. The social machinery that we have constructed as a consequence seems to be extremely efficient in furthering the material well being of its exponents but does that unmistakably entail the success of specialization in all its different realms of application?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In spite of the fact that our educational institutions produce individuals of remarkable competence in their respective fields, they are still nonetheless characterized by a general imbecility when construed outside their domains of expertise. Latent qualities and tendencies that might contribute to a natural appraisal of the world is left unheeded since the road to economic prosperity could simply be paved by performing one particular task exceptionally well. This proposition nonetheless does not imply aspiring to the unachievable ideal of mastering all disciplines simultaneously but that one should always seek knowledge not as a means to an end but as an end in itself. The unquenchable thirst for wisdom and truth that we observe in children is ruthlessly suppressed so that one might impose a systematic form of edification that seems more befitting in a complex world but this I am afraid is achieved at the great peril of their individual curiosity. Although it is indispensable to eventually choose a primary academic venture that one might pursue throughout the course of his life, it is also equally necessary to retain a generally inquisitive nature which constitutes the very essence of being human. But how exactly should one go about doing this?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is when I attempted to answer this predicament that I fully realised the stupendous importance of the forgotten art of reading. The reason I suppose a book can ideally foster and even recuperate this dormant curiosity that every individual invariably conceals is because the former is often a culmination of some comprehensive investigation that spans a wide range of the human enterprise. Any book that speaks to the soul of an individual must always contain this element of generality for it is precisely this that unites the diversity of human interest in all its multitude of manifestations. Every endeavour that people have undertaken from time immemorial has always been dedicated to the furtherance of this interest regardless of the formidable tribulations that it might entail. Thus it seemed to me that the gift of inquiry which man has been fortunately endowed with was the most salient quality that characterized him and from which all of our creative pursuits inexorably derived their profuse vitality. The reason our forebears were even remotely capable of erecting this monumental civilization that we take for granted is because of their unshakeable resolve to venture forth into the treacherous lands of the unknown whose ambivalent nature makes it simultaneously a source of great promise and unprecedented threat. This fidelity for their own individual nature that was single-handedly responsible for all our great accomplishments was not borne out of material avarice or from the ignoble satisfaction of being superior to ones fellow peers. It was rather a consequence of an inexplicable feeling of contentment they obtained from seeking something that they believed to be immensely meaningful. A meaning that they had come to discover within their own hearts for the things that we most need are often found in places we are least likely to look.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Plight of Modern Dialectic</title>
      <link>https://noumenalnotions.space/essays/the_plight_of_modern_dialectic/</link>
      <guid>https://noumenalnotions.space/essays/the_plight_of_modern_dialectic/</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Dec 2020 22:14:00 IST</pubDate>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;karamazov&#34;&gt;Karamazov&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In his last publication The Brothers Karamazov, Fyodor Dostoevsky writes about the murder of a debauched old man named Fyodor Pavlovitch Karamazov who begets three sons in the course of his lifetime. The story, for the most part,
enunciates an elaborate drama involving these three brothers and intertwines Dostoevskys propositions about Religion and Existentialism in the dialogue between various characters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The book containing about 800 pages of dramatic prose proves to be quite a laborious read but nonetheless offers extremely profound insights about the nature of human existence. Unlike philosophers who usually prefer to express
fundamental truths about life in abstract parlance, Dostoevsky chooses to embody his opinions in the personality of his characters to achieve a much more nuanced and pragmatic orientation towards the problems he attempts to answer.
Expressions of the former category, although might be deemed as a much more efficient way of communicating, will never be able to achieve the complexity of the latter kind of symbolic story telling and this I believe is one of the
reasons for why Brothers Karamazov is regarded as a seminal work in the history of Russia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the course of my diligent perusal to understand this work of literature, I inadvertently also happened to notice how Dostoevsky introduced his ideas to the fellow reader. Around the last part of the book, one of the brothers called
Ivan Karamazov is revealed to suffer from a mental delirium and experiences severe hallucinations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The devil, masquerading as a well dressed noble figure, appears to Ivan and incessantly questions about his former choices. The conversation that ensues in the next 50 pages or so involves profound theological discussions about God and essentially presents us with the Devils side of the religious narrative. The devil proclaims that he was predestined to follow the path of abomination and construes his act of defiance as what constitutes reality that exists. He implores Ivan to question the very concept of free will within the religious framework and subsequently endeavors to illustrate how the morbid aspects of life are precisely from whence goodness draws its supreme value.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In spite of being overwhelmingly influenced by Dostoevskys supposition about the necessity of evil, I also realized that this attempt to expound one of the fundamental inconsistency within theology was at cross purposes with his own
agenda. Dostoevsky always considered religious belief structures as indispensable in a stable society and regarded it as the ultimate source of human morality. I was immensely perplexed on why Dostoevsky would venture to
deconstruct his own arguments but after a considerable amount of deliberation, I discovered why he chose to do this. The reason I think Dostoevsky possess the hallmark of a profound thinker is because he does not commit the intellectual impertinence of desperately trying to undermine the oppositions argument but rather assiduously strives to understand it. He acknowledges why the opposition is inclined towards that conclusion and goes on to present his own views on the matter to achieve an unbiased perspective on the object of discussion. It seems to me that The Brothers Karamazov, in addition to being fraught with controversial surmises, also contains extremely powerful lessons about the conduct of dialectic which are all the more necessary in the contemporary epoch
of mass communication.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-other&#34;&gt;The Other&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to understand why I believe Dostoevskys writings have far reaching implications on modern discourse, I suppose it would also require an understanding of the nature of interpersonal relationships and for this
I resort back to my readings of an eminent French philosopher named Jean Paul Sartre.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sartre is posthumously proclaimed as the philosopher of freedom among the citizens of France and the reason behind such a title is obviously his attempt to offer a phenomenological explication on the concept of freedom. Sartres
endeavor to construct a phenomenological ontology, as he liked to call it, that provides an adequate account of reality has had incredible influence over philosophical circles and made him one of the most famous exponents of
existential phenomenology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When reading Sartre, his inveterate obsession with freedom became quite evident and I very quickly acquired the impression that this is what drove him to derive a radical definition of human consciousness that was conducive to free will and which later served as the basis for his ontology. Sartre simply
conceives consciousness as nothing more than a revealing intuition that exists solely in virtue of its relation to the objects of the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the very outset, he completely rejects Descartes cogito ergo sum and proposes that consciousness cannot be self conscious by positing itself as an object of reflection but rather is only aware of itself implicitly by being
conscious of other objects. By this sleight of hand, Sartre escapes the fallacy of an infinite regress and furthermore attributes a peculiar quality to consciousness that allows it to transcend the deterministic laws of causality and ensures its freedom of action. Since consciousness has no existence in and
of itself, it can maintain a paradoxical state of being what it is not and not being what it is to quote Sartres words.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This definition of consciousness, in addition to being one of the most strikingly original postulates in metaphysics, also entails extraordinary implications in the realm of intersubjective relationships. In providing us
with a rather peculiar account of human consciousness Sartre has, to some extent, assured its autonomous nature by positing that it exists in a constant state of becoming but what does that imply about how others perceive us?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Clearly our perception of others is never quite the same as we see ourselves. In spite of the fact that we acknowledge the qualities in ourselves that we usually regard as perennial, we never seem to exclusively identify ourselves with it since the essence of our subjectivity is much more than a unity of our thoughts and past actions. But this essence, however, is inaccessible to any external being that perceives us and is consequently resolved into a finite conception in the means to apprehend us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is what Sartres most quoted maxim that Hell is other people tries to illustrate. When one is conscious of being perceived by the other, he feels that his ever complex subjectivity is, in some sense, delimited to an unsophisticated finitude. He becomes conscious of the attempt that his constant state of becoming is perpetually reduced to a state of mere being. And the realization of this simple idea, I believe, would have substantial consequences in the quality of intellectual discourse because trying to encapsulate the subjective nature of ones being seems to me to characterize one of the most
salient aspects of human dialectic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;modern-dialectic&#34;&gt;Modern Dialectic&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At first sight, it might seem incredibly far fetched to make a connection between two ingenious philosophers who lived decades apart from each other but both Dostoevsky and Sartre understood something quite profound about human
existence that the modern world has began to forget.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In spite of the fact that Dostoevsky disdained the nihilistic standpoint, The Brothers Karamazov contains extraordinarily convincing arguments for renouncing a meaningful life in favor of nihilism. The reason for employing such a paradoxical style of writing is clearly because the authors intention is
simply not to proselytize the reader to accept his theological beliefs but rather is to present his proposition in light of various other perspectives that are equally plausible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, this does not reflect the fact that he thinks his opinions are untenable in any sense but merely instantiates his proclivity to challenge his own ideas to the absolute extreme to refine his conception of the ultimate truth. This tireless curiosity for truth that we observe in Dostoevsky is precisely what the modern dialect has lost due to its arrogance. Intellectuals and laymen alike are so accustomed to looking at the world from their standpoint that they scarcely ever notice how the other sees the world.  As a result, one constantly reduces people to some half baked preconceived notion that appeals to his prejudice, ignoring quite blatantly that every single individual conceals an entire universe inside of them. Every opinion that is voiced has merely become a covert struggle to display ones verbal competence instead of it being used as a tool to expound the truth underlying reality. If it is one thing that modernity could learn from revolutionary thinkers like Dostoevsky, it is their unbreakable fidelity for the truth of the matter. The only ideology they pledge allegiance to has always been the truth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes this allegiance comes at the expense of renouncing ones most cherished beliefs but no price is too high pay for being disillusioned by the verities of actuality. But the truth however does not exist only in realm of mere objectivity and this seems to me is where Dostoevsky and Sartre meet. Although I could understand why Dostoevsky did not want to dismantle the opposition with petty tactics, I couldn&amp;rsquo;t fully explain why he didn&amp;rsquo;t choose to embody his suppositions in abstract language.  For a long time, I merely attributed this choice of expression as arbitrary but
it was Sartres account of the Other that resuscitated a long buried train of thought. One can never get to the bottom of things unless one considers the subjective aspect of dialectic and this perhaps is the most striking
realization I have had reading Dostoevsky. By perpetually assaulting his own presuppositions, the age old Russian author not only presents an unbiased view to the reader but also tries to comprehend his opponents in all their
essentiality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moving past the realm of mere objective refutations, he constantly endeavors to obtain the reason for why a particular thought is appealing to man of said background. Simply put, Dostoevsky tries desperately not to reduce the other to his own presumption of them and consequently strives to refute that Hell is
other people.
One could obviously raise the objection that this is a fools errand. That one can never really capture the unadulterated essence of a persons true nature and clearly one cannot. But nonetheless, it seems to me that this still doesn&amp;rsquo;t justify forsaking the endeavor because it does not mean one can never get
close.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most dialectic that is often encountered in the modern world fails to consider the idiosyncratic aspect of a particular opinion and usually seeks to convince the opposition about the falsity of his convictions by deploying logical fallacies and other de-constructive techniques. This disregard for the other
steers the argument away from the truth of the subject and merely transforms it to an intellectual fist fight were both the parties make use of subversive tactics to undermine each other, not realizing that neither one of them has
imparted a modicum of wisdom on the other. Directing ones attention to the subjective side of an argument might seem to take us backwards because reason has always grounded itself in the objective realm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But it is also worthwhile to remember that there are innumerable areas that
exist within the domain of knowledge where reason cannot penetrate. And the only way that one could at least try to comprehend these provinces of ineffability is by putting himself in the others shoe. As Harper Lee writes
quite eloquently &amp;lsquo;You can never really understand a person until you consider things from his point of view until you climb into his skin and walk around in it&amp;rsquo; and it&amp;rsquo;s about time that we started getting under each other&amp;rsquo;s skins the right way.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
